It was muted.
Did you get it? Did it go on? Yes. Now it's on.
Okay.
Hello. Okay, let me not trip. That's hot.
That work?
It works, yeah. I think they're going to turn it on now.
Okay. Oh, this is on. It's hot. All right, here we go.
Good morning, everybody, and thank you for coming to our session.
Let me put this on.
My Madonna skills here are waning. There we go. Okay.
Our session is
titled--
This is supposed to be the first slide of the talk.
I'm trying to-
Oh
... find the mouse, which is not on the screen.
Oh, it's on this one, though.
I see it there.
Yeah.
I just have to get it back over here. There it is.
And there is a PDF. Oh, no, that's for Friday. Sorry.
I didn't know you-
We're good.
I think we're good.
Okay.
There we go. Thanks so much.
Okay. Yeah.
So welcome, folks. Let's go through these first couple of ones.
Thanks to our sponsors. This session is "Sustaining the Geo
Biodiversity Data Ecosystem: Standards-Driven Approaches to Long-Term
Resilience." Those are the co-organizers, some of whom are
also speakers in this session, and we're all members
of a group called the International Partners for the Digital Extended Specimen,
which I will introduce in just a second.
A quick overview to the timing of this session.
I'm going to give just a quick introduction to
our work and to the topics in this session,
and then I'll pass it off to each of the speakers who will give
12-minute presentations, and we're going to save all the questions till the end.
So we have a discussion at the end.
I encourage you to stick around, but that's the plan.
So,
the group that I mentioned, the International Partners for the Digital Extended
Specimen, we are focusing our efforts right now on
sustainability and collaboration in a time of uncertainty.
And
through this talk, in the next few minutes, I'll just briefly mention who we are,
some of the things that we've done, this notion of
sustainability and how challenging it is, and then
just a little bit about where we're taking these ideas.
So our
goal as IPDES is to enable research that contributes to new
discoveries that help address the societal challenges associated with the
biodiversity crisis. The mission is broader than any one infrastructure.
It's about coordinating a globally integrated network of stakeholders and
connecting biodiversity data and knowledge through both technical and social
infrastructure, data, tools, standards, people, and working practices.
This is
a paper that we published four years or so ago now that
kind of builds off of ideas that came out of North America and
Europe around the extended specimen and the digital specimen.
And so we
combined and advanced some of those into the digital extended specimen,
which we feel is a useful way to think about the full ecosystem.
We start with the physical specimen and a digital record, and then the extended
specimen that links that record to additional information and relationships.
And it's a connected architecture, and standards, of course, allow that
information to move easily through these layers.
So when we think about sustainability,
over time and through these various discussions, three major themes
have emerged, three major needs. The first is technology and infrastructure,
and the digital extended specimen can provide a unifying framework for this
very distributed landscape. It helps us identify the critical pieces, understand
how they connect, and demonstrates why sustained investment across those pieces
matters for integrated data and high-impact research.
Another important part is obviously the people.
So,
sustainable infrastructure requires a resilient and inclusive community, supporting
careers and expertise, shared governance, and investment in the people and skills
that actually make the connections work.
We can preserve servers and software, but without the people who understand the
data, standards, collections, and relationships, we haven't preserved the
infrastructure.
And of course, funding, a hot topic on all of our minds always.
Traditional funding sources are increasingly uncertain, so we need to think much
more broadly about the portfolio that supports biodiversity infrastructure,
longer-term public investment, philanthropy, international partnerships, existing
organizations and infrastructures, and potentially new models that recognize the
socioeconomic value created by biodiversity data.
The important point is that sustainability probably won't come from finding one
replacement funding source. It will come from building a more diverse and resilient
model, and we've seen that in various projects and talks, I think, this week
already. So how do we sustain all of this?
Jutta Buschbaum, one of our
co-leaders here, has a good point.
We have a business case, a community, a track record, strong partners, and an
emerging value return mechanism.
So while we feel that this is-
that we have a lot of work to do. We have gone a long way already.
We have a lot behind us, a lot that we can work with.
So,
it's groups like this, International Partners for the Digital Specimen, and
groups like the Biodiversity Collections Network, or BCON.
We've put together some
next steps and outlined some directions that the community has advanced
and some directions we can go going forward.
And in these
figures from recent publications,
these are all topics that we know well, and
continuing to keep these at the front of our mind will help us with
sustainability. And none of these pieces work well in isolation, right?
So sustainability requires us to think about them as part of the same
system.
So what we've done through IPDS is brought
variations of this series, of this session that you're about to see now, to
various audiences. We started in June with the Digital Data
Conference, which iDigBio put together, and recordings of that are online.
Andy Bentley, one of our members, brought it to SPInACH a few weeks
ago in South Africa. Here we are at Chadwick, and for those of you in Australia or
virtually,
we'll be represented at the ICOM-NatHist Conference. Thank you, Ellie, for that.
And
the idea then is to synthesize and to bring these ideas together in a webinar
that we'll produce later this year, ideally.
So, stay tuned for that. But each of
these conferences were based in different parts of the world with slightly
different audiences. So we're hoping those different perspectives provide some
bigger ideas and things for us to move forward with.
So, thank you for that. I'm going to pass it on to Joe Miller for now, and
stick around for the discussion at the end.
And, oh, yes, I'm going to get rid of that and
.
Good morning, everyone.
Yeah. This morning I'd like to spend a few minutes talking about GBIF and
sustainability and how we approach it from
the secretariat and how we try to apply sustainable ideas.
I guess the bottom line is to see how we can bring in money and help
spread that money around to help us all out.
I guess the foundational thing about GBIF is we're an intergovernmental
organization celebrating our 25th year.
This is a picture from last year in Colombia.
Next week, we'll have our governing board here in Oslo.
We expect to have 120 people here next week, 33 voting
participants. So I
don't know of any other international organization such as ours who has 40
member countries that pay every year to the same biodiversity infrastructure.
And our funding from national investments has been flat and
slightly growing over the last five years. We have a governance mechanism.
We have the secretariat, in Copenhagen, and we have...
Oh, right in the middle of all that. That's a little scary, isn't it?
We have a governing board who I report to.
We have committees that we
give advice to the secretariat, and it all works quite well, and we'll have a nice
fun meeting next week discussing all that.
But one of the major things, as you all know about, is our peer-reviewed
publications using GBIF-mediated data.
This is really the core of
how GBIF works. This was done way before I got there.
A brilliant idea implemented. So you share data with GBIF,
we put DOIs on things coming in, going out, and we can track
how that data is used. And this is very
important to not only funders, the data producers, and the data
users. Here's a really good example.
This specimen was in an herbarium in Togo for a long time.
We received money in our first round of the BID program, Biodiversity Information
for Development.
Pierre Rageat, the herbarium director, was part of a grant that
mobilized this particular specimen.
That grant was come to us. This BID program is funded by the European Commission,
so if you're a European
taxpayer, your contribution helped this.
This specimen was shared
as part of that project, and then it was used in this
2023 paper by some Chinese authors
that cited it in a species distribution modeling.
And there are literally billions of examples of this, right?
Hundreds of millions of records are being used, eight peer-reviewed publications
every day and growing using GBIF data, and we can track all this.
It's just brilliant, and that really helps with the publication.
So the added layer to that is policy.
It's a bit more difficult to say specifically that
that specimen was used
in the IPBES report. But this is, of course, the 2023 IPBES
report was very important to our community, outlining the
billions of euros that
we waste in the world because of invasive species, right?
It's a huge,
not only financial, but of course, environmental impact of invasive species.
We did a citation tracking in that, looking at the papers that
were cited in this, because this uses secondary literature.
It doesn't do research itself, but it cites papers that do research.
31 of the 32 messages
in this report are
based or include GBIF-mediated data use in
peer-reviewed publications. So if you shared data before 2023,
it probably was cited in an IPBES report.
I double-checked with Daniel, this
exact paper was not used in the report because it was written in
2023 around the same time as this report.
So be assured
that if you're sharing data, it's being used for science and policy.
So as I mentioned, our financing is mainly by a
financial model that was put together in a memorandum of understanding.
It's renewed every five years, but it's based on GDP, so it's a fair
spreading out the contributions based on the ability of a country to pay.
So as I mentioned,
this has been flat or slowly growing over the last five years, but
we've been able to leverage this, and our budget actually
is twice as big as it was five years ago because we're leveraging
that stability
of these national contributions.
So our budget has doubled through contributions, through European Commission
grants, through foundations, special purpose funds, which some
of them are just actually large gifts that we can use as needed
to support our work program. And all of this goes straight into the work program to
support this. So I'll be telling the governing board next
week that they're getting a return on investment of 100%.
Every dollar they put in, they're getting €2.
I'll say it in euros tomorrow, next week.
But every euro that is contributed, there's €2 worth of work
program effort. And that, I think, we can keep growing.
But we don't want to be selfish as well because we do know that there is
lots of capacity. That's kind of a sad way of saying it, but there's lots of good
people who are underfunded and need funding to do your work, right?
And that's certainly true.
But we do have the ability to pass some of that on.
We, of course, have-- I hope you know of the CESS program,
Capacity Enhancement Support Program, which supports nodes in projects.
And we also have the BID program, which is our flagship program, which
this year we're funding. It's about a million euros worth of projects.
That's the money that will be spent this year around the world.
So in total,
approximately 25% of our budget is going
to activities here, either contractors that we support around the world
or projects or CESS projects in all six continents.
So we're spreading. So I'll tell the governing board next week,
for every euro you're spending, another euro is being
brought into the system, and 50% of that euro is actually going out the door to
support other projects.
And longer-term sustainability, we really focused on
driving this, and Libby kind of mentioned the
need to be important to policy. And for the past five years,
and even more so, but it's really coming to a head now, we've been driving
this relationship between data policy and funding.
We've developed a really good relationship with the Convention on Biological
Diversity and the Global Environment Facility,
World Bank, UNDP, these organizations that manage the
money that is used to do large-scale
conservation efforts around the world because they all need data, they all need
capacity, and what we do as a GBIF network enables that.
So this is something that is really coming to a head now with the start of
GEF 9, which is this new program of funds
that are coming out later this year, the Global Biodiversity Framework Fund,
which will be a next round of those coming out in a few weeks.
And of course, many of you know the COP 17 next month.
We're really working closely with the
Technical Support Coordination Center, these regional bodies, and we will
be embedding GBIF, that's you as well, GBIF activities
in these regional meetings.
So
this was a highlight for me last year.
Astrid Schmucker, the Executive Secretary of the CBD, she wrote this
notification, as they call it. "Given the relevance and the work undertaken by GBIF
to the implementation of the KBMBF and to the Convention on Biological
Diversity, I encourage all parties," that's all countries, "to join GBIF as
national participants." So this is my lead now when talking to countries.
It works a little bit. It's a tough sell to get countries to join, especially in
this framework, but this is very convincing.
We also had a mention by the
Global Environment Facility, the GEF, the funding mechanism, this at Substa,
on a slide saying that GBIF is a key infrastructure in their
thinking. Of course, this is the framework of the
CBD, and we've done the mapping. Many of the
targets are aligned to the work that we do as a community, whether
it's collections or citizen science or camera traps.
Especially these highlighted targets, especially
target six on invasive species, of course, is a very important one in
which GBIF media data is part of the headline indicator.
So your data is flowing into all of these, and our job is to making sure all the
countries know this. And some know it because, hopefully,
recently your country
put in their seventh national reports to the CBD.
So we've been going through these national reports and seeing how
countries have been mentioning GBIF.
They're using probably GBIF, but do they know they're using GBIF?
Do they know they have a national node? It's very heterogeneous.
Across these reports, two-thirds of them mention GBIF
across all the targets, but GBIF data is not used in all the targets, so there's a
mix-match there.
But there is growing uptake. Some
mention GBIF, some mention the BID program, some mention the national node.
Fantastic. But there's often in countries a disconnect
within the government across these
different things, and our goal is to try to tie the GBIF node with the FAO
focal point, the CBD focal point, the GEF focal point, and get them all in the same
room. So we're hoping that the eighth report in a few years will
really include
more detailed use and explicit mention, recognition
of the work that we're doing.
And these are just a sampling of three mechanisms that
the GEF have that we're looking into now.
So, the agency-led programs are these GEF 9 ones.
This is a new set of money, new programs coming out, that we will
work to get GBIF programs embedded in, like BID programs, regional
support,
infrastructure support for the secretariat as well, built in.
We'll try to build in work on the data model into these type of things, because the
GBIF is all about sampling, right?
And what we're doing through Tidewig and all this is making sure that we're able
to bring sampling monitoring event.
Star pipelines are something specific for countries, and they get to decide what to
do with that. So we want countries to integrate with that.
So what we have is a suite of
project ideas that we are giving to regional
support centers and with countries and say, "Here, embed this in
your application, and we'll work with you to make it successful." And one of those
that we're very excited about is
piloting a multi-taxonomy
in South Africa. So this is coming out of the work on the new
infrastructure. We're able to do much more things with this clever infrastructure
that Tim and Fede and the team have put together.
So we now can
use the South African national taxonomy, and we indexed, as a
pilot demo,
South African botanical data
with their own taxonomy. So for example, this, we'll be
going public with this, so this isn't public, at the COP next month.
But here you can see this
particular occurrence is known by riccardii in South Africa, but according
to Catalog of Life, it has a different name, but the
synonymy is there. So we're delivering the data South Africa
needs for their reports in their own taxonomy, and this is a major
blocking point for countries in their reporting.
So this, I think, will be a major improvement.
And if you need something to do over the weekend, we wrote a paper.
I invite you to download and read that.
And the overview, there, Fede has it there.
We tried to hit all the topics that we cover at the secretariat, so
I hope you enjoy it. Thank you.
Thank you to Joe and Fede for speaking.
Next up, I welcome Dr. Adrian. Dr. Adrian, your talk is
after.
Oh, yeah. No mouse here. That is-
It's on the other screen as well.
Which one do I go? Maybe this one. There we go. Okay.
They're
fine now.
Wait, so? Mm-hmm.
You have to click on...
Let's
see.
All right.
Let me start with this picture.
In
1914, Sir Ernest Shackleton
set sail
to Antarctica for an expedition to cross
Antarctica and to explore it.
But in 1915,
there was a disaster. They were
stuck in the pack ice around
Antarctica. They tried to free the ship, but they failed.
And the pack ice really crushed the ship.
So Shackleton immediately took action, and
he abandoned basically the expedition, and
he focused on saving his crew. He was sailing with
people,
and they abandoned the ship, and they
created a camp on the ice.
And they stayed there for about four, nearly five
months. But then spring arrived,
and yeah, the ice melted,
and, well, they had to move there because
there was not enough ice left.
So they took the
small boats they had, the rescue boats, so
three of them, and they set sail to the nearest
island.
That took six days, and then they arrived at Elephant
Island, which was a small island, inhabited.
But at least for the time being, they were safe.
But Shackleton realized that there was no chance that
people would ever find them there,
because it was very far from the rest of the
inhabited world,
and they had no radio at that time, of course.
So
he decided to take five of his crew, take the
smallest boat,
and set sail
to South Georgia Island,
which was a journey of 800 miles.
And it took 17 days. They only had
very limited navigation instruments,
only a sextant,
but they managed to do that.
It was very difficult to land there, because there was a big
hurricane going on, so it took them two days.
They suffered severely from
frostbite. The water was contaminated with seawater.
So they were in pretty bad condition.
And they arrived at the wrong side of the island, at the south part of the island,
where no people were there, and
they had no chance of sailing further to the north part.
So
Ernest Shackleton, together with two of his crew who were in the best
condition,
went by foot
to the other side of the island, to a whale station there,
36 hours on foot,
and they managed to do that. So they
managed to get there, get help.
And at the end,
Shackleton
created a new expedition to rescue the rest of his crew,
which was about
August 1916.
So the crew survived for 22 months-
On the island, living on hunting seals and
drinking melting ice, et cetera.
So all the crew at the end survived.
And why
am I telling this story now?
Because this is all about resilience.
Resilience is not about avoiding that crash that happens,
but it is about taking immediate action.
So he took immediate action to make sure that he saved his
crew.
And not only that, but it's also about never losing hope
and about focusing on preserving your most precious assets, in
this case, the crew. So it's all about resilience.
Now,
talking about resilience for our global community.
Our global community faces a lot of disasters at the moment,
and
what is important is knowing what we are losing and where it
is moving,
and
how to protect what remains. And specimens play an important role in
that because specimens provide the evidence that you can use
to
see what the decline of species is,
how they move over time.
So they are important for
biodiversity loss,
but they are also important for climate change studies, because they show how
species evolve over time and adapt to changing
conditions. And also for health risks,
because the specimens contain information about pathogens and the
relationships with humans and other
organisms.
But there is an issue
with specimens,
because specimens are hosted in
institutions scattered all over the world,
in cabinets,
stored, and it's quite fragile.
So,
we need to do something to
make them better findable and
usable.
Also,
the specimens
data
is scattered all over the place,
and we need to make sure that data becomes
better available.
So the data is no longer a luxury. It's really necessary
for our survival.
Now, a challenge that we have is that in Europe, only
10% of the specimens is currently digitized,
and that's of an estimated 1.5 billion
specimens.
So yeah, we really need to work on
mobilizing data and large-scale digitization.
And that's part of the mission of DiSSCo, to
scale that up, to industrialize the digitization of the specimens,
and to make that available as one homogenous,
uniform dataset that you can use.
So DiSSCo is a transformative infrastructure.
So it
synchronizes between all these scattered datasets,
create one big European virtual collection,
with FAIR-compliant data.
So it's findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable, both by
humans, but also by machines. And it's machine actionable, so
machines can act upon the data, can enrich the data
with linkages to derived and related data,
like sequence information, literature, et cetera.
So,
we can connect the data or reconnect the data, the specimen data,
with all that extra information that's available on the internet.
And we can do it on a very large scale.
And the core of the infrastructure is the DiSSCo Extended Specimen,
which is an actionable and citable unit.
It is a FAIR DiSSCo object,
kind of a container of all the information that we know about the specimen,
not only the catalog information, but also all the linkages to the
external information.
It has its own persistent identifier, a DOI, that you can
use for referencing that, for citing that.
So that's the core of the infrastructure.
And,
DiSSCo,
because it is an infrastructure, it can go to
project cycle dependency. Often now, data is
generated in
funded projects, and
that funding is finite. When that funding ends, it becomes
difficult to preserve that data.
And
because DiSSCo is a long-term infrastructure with funding from
the countries, we go
beyond that dependency.
So the data becomes much more resilient.
And to do that,
we
follow the ERIC model, European Research Infrastructure Consortium,
which is a legal
body supported by the European Commission,
which includes
member states as their members.
And this provides a legal body to
engage in funding projects,
but also provides the long-term governance.
The member states have institutional commitments, so
commitments on a national scale to preserve biodiversity,
but also the financial commitments, the contributions to the
infrastructure, and also the governance commitments.
So
making sure
that the national
initiatives are
aligned with the international, the European
infrastructure.
Going towards the ERIC is a long journey.
It's about 10 years. So creating an
European infrastructure takes about 10 years.
We started with the project phase,
where we
designed the infrastructure,
started building the connections, building the first nodes, and
the first services.
This is followed by a transition phase, where we aim to
consolidate
the nodes infrastructure,
and finalize the
policy documents and the legal documents.
And we are now in a phase that we are ending that.
We just
submitted step two submission to become an ERIC, and we are
now waiting for the final decision on that, and we hope to launch the ERIC
in next year.
We have six countries as founding members, so it's a
very good start. We need at least three to start.
And I think many more countries will follow in the
coming years.
So this goes, it's a very large initiative.
1.5 billion specimens are our target,
and we have currently more than 400 institutions involved from 23
countries.
So it's a very big initiative to go to this one
European collection.
And that's my presentation.
There's no time for questions.
Thanks, Wouter. Next up is Jose Fortes.
Excuse me.
Good morning, everyone.
So, I'm a cyberinfrastructure designer, and
through interactions with my colleagues in the IPDAS,
the group that Libby alluded to, iDigBio, and
some of you in the audience,
I face this question of how does cyberinfrastructure
design change when we take sustainability as a
first-order consideration?
And so
to answer this question and share what I think with you,
it's worth thinking about infrastructures in different
domains that are very successful at sustaining themselves.
Think of
radio stations if you're
from my generation
and can relate to that particular old radio,
or think about Spotify if in the younger generation.
And what you see there is that there is a process of
aggregation of data from very
distinct sources around the globe.
And this data, i.e., music, podcasts, and
so forth, is made available through a variety of
channels, some of which are free, typically the public radio
stations,
some of which are charged, some of which come with ads
so that they can support themselves.
And all of this operates in a single infrastructure.
So,
you may or may not know how that infrastructure works.
I don't know it in great extent, but every single time you
listen to a song or a podcast, there is a tiny amount of
money that goes to the producer of that content.
And so there's an ecosystem that functions extremely well,
of data creators, content creators, aggregators,
distributors. And the important thing is that the
users and all the players in this ecosystem have
knobs
or
buttons that they can click to essentially
determine how the entire thing functions.
And everyone is able to
pay if they need to pay,
get income if they deserve the income.
And there's an economy that this ecosystem functions within
that is quite successful. So if we take a view
that in cyber-- By the way,
as the disclaimer says, I'm not advocating
for the end of
what we as scientists very much appreciate, which is open data
access,
and for purposes of science work,
free access to the data.
That's not my intent here.
My intent is to account for the
diversity of scenarios where
there are costs involved, and these have to be funded, and there are
parties that
may have to be charged. But for scientific
purposes, I think the open science, free science is the way to go.
So,
if you think about biodiversity research,
nowadays, increasingly what we do,
what you do, I'm a cyberinfrastructure guy,
is you access data from multiple sources.
You have to discover it, you have to integrate it, you have to correlate it.
And then depending on the problem that you're trying to solve,
you do additional work, and the data sources may change with the
problem, and so forth. So, this should all look
familiar to you. We like to get
specimen records, genetic information, weather
information. The extended specimen concept is all about
creating these
elaborate linkages of data that enable specific problems to
be addressed.
So
please move forward.
I want to jump from that big picture to some conclusions that I think,
hopefully, are easy to reach. One is that we
have to
work within this large ecosystem with multiple services,
data sources, and providers.
And that
at the end of the day, if you're bringing together these different sources,
you're federating a lot of organizations.
Some may be small, some may be big, global, regional, and so
forth.
And so if you want to create cyberinfrastructure that is sustainable,
you can only do that if the ecosystem itself is
sustainable. So there's no point in having a sustained
cyberinfrastructure if no one is going to use it, and vice
versa, if the cyberinfrastructure is to be sustained, those
who use it need to contribute to that sustainability.
So historically,
what we
have grown accustomed to living with
is this very good model, which I endorse completely and
have worked within for many years.
You have essentially an entity. In the US, it's the National
Science Foundation, but other countries have equivalent, that funds on
a periodic basis, three to five years at a time,
the university or the labs or
other entities. And if they do well, this gets
renewed and sustainability follows from good
performance. And good performance is measured in
scientific production.
Now, this is great.
It's the one I endorse, but things are changing,
and there are other models that are emerging.
We already had
talks that alluded to this in this conference, but
there are cases where the users have to do
subscriptions.
There are cases where there are app
advertisements
that support the operation of the infrastructure,
and there is increasingly discussions on models that
entail paying as you go,
and
seeking sponsorships and partnerships with
industry and other sources of
funds. So we're going to go from a
situation where the funders are distinct from the users
to a situation where
the customers, I no longer call them users,
are actually directly funding the activity of the infrastructure.
But the main point here is that this is not
a one-way
absolute trend. I think what's going to happen is that we're going to
have hybrids
of
centralized funding, customer-based funding, et
cetera.
And so if you accept the fact that we're going to have these hybrids,
cyberinfrastructure has to accommodate all of these options.
So
if we think about what these options have in common,
even if it is the funding from the National Science Foundation, for
example, we have to report everything.
If it is
a pay-as-you-go, you have to report what you have used in
terms of data services and so forth, so you are responsible for paying
for it. If it is a centralized agency that funds the
entire infrastructure, you have to report how many papers you've written.
Joe Miller showed what GBIF has to report at a large scale, in
some sense, to justify this recurring funding.
By the way, I'm very jealous of GBIF
and Disco.
But in any case,
if you accept that regardless of the model that is being used, that you
have to
do all the collection of data, all the tracking,
you have to make sure that you know what's charged,
and how the revenue from those charges gets distributed
to ensure sustainability,
then the cyberinfrastructure has to support this.
And in the past, we never thought about this, or at least I never thought about it.
But when sustainability comes into the picture,
I think it becomes extremely important.
So, you can think of the big question being, how does the
biodiversity ecosystem economy work, and
how does the cyberinfrastructure support it?
So you can think of
that economy implying that the
cyberinfrastructure, in addition to having to do the technical
orchestration of multiple providers of content
for biodiversity research, now has to worry about
a component that does the economic orchestration.
Now, this is not very glamorous for us as scientists,
but it's something that we need to communicate as a
community to the cyber infrastructure builders.
TADWIG is an organization that addresses standards,
and you can imagine how hard it is if we
build this economy and there's not a collection of standards
that enables everyone to play together.
So,
the good news are that there are a lot of these services that are already
deployed,
credit card charges,
billing services, and so forth, that we can adopt
if we have the time and put in the effort to think about this.
But there are other things that are unique to the community.
Those are things like, what do you charge for?
Is it a record, or is it an image, or
is it bytes,
or is it a complete service? I really don't know.
And
these are conversations that I think need to be had.
But there's a lot of things that I'm not going to read here that
entail
quite a bit of cyber infrastructure and investment.
And,
if
you think of these multitude of services that exist around the world,
as
smaller entities than an iDigBio or a GBIF,
they're really not in a position to build all of this.
So we need to come up with ways in which these folks can
interface with the ecosystem and
derive the revenue they need to sustain themselves,
and function in a relatively transparent manner.
A quick example, this is something we're building at ChatBio.
It uses a bunch of agents to access different resources.
So this is very
related to the picture that I presented before, where
there is a biodiversity ecosystem where different
problems require different sources.
Those that are circled are supported by ChatBio right now.
And just as a timid
approach to what I described in this talk,
we try to implement all the tracking needed
to make sure we can have a sense for how many resources are
used, what the user value
provided is.
So,
if we had a session,
or we could look at things for all sessions, for all
users and so forth, we know exactly which data source has been
accessed and who did what,
and
get a sense for the value of the interaction.
So I'm out of time, but the conclusions hopefully are
clear now.
Cyber infrastructure sustainability is the same as ecosystem
sustainability. They go hand in hand.
We need to track everything that is done, who does what,
for what purposes, how should revenue be distributed?
And to answer these questions, I think this calls for
collaboration between the two sides, the biodiversity cyber infrastructure,
and the
cyber infrastructure--
the biodiversity ecosystem, and the cyber infrastructure community.
Thank you.
You keep this or I'll-- it's just a video next.
Oh.
All right. Next up, we have a video.
So
let me find my mouse.
Okay, so this is pre-recorded from Andrea Thomer.
Hi, my name is Andrea Thomer. I'm a professor of information science at the
University of Arizona, where I study and try to support the maintenance and
development of knowledge infrastructures in the natural sciences.
I'm also the co-PI of CESAAR, the Center for Earth and Extraterrestrial Sample
Analysis and Archive, and the co-chair of the Physical Sample Curation Cluster in
the Earth Science Information Partners organization, also known as ESIP.
If you haven't heard of ESIP, it's the earth science version of TADWIG.
In my talk today, I'll be discussing some data infrastructure resilience efforts in
the earth sciences in the hope that this will contribute to future collaboration
between the earth and biodiversity informatics communities.
This is an admittedly US-centric talk, but I hope it'll still be of interest to
folks in the international TADWIG community.
So I'm going to start off with a quote.
"It's hard to care for that much data, actually.
And there's no money to do it. There's no money for maintenance. It's not sexy.
Nobody's name gets put on it like the wing of a building."
So this quote is from an interview study I published a few years ago.
My collaborator and I were speaking with collections database managers at
natural history museums and other kinds of memory institutions.
We were interested in understanding how they sustain their databases over long
periods of time. And the answer is they sustain them with great effort and very
little support.
I'm starting with this quote because it sums up the state of affairs for
infrastructure maintenance, even in the best of times.
We rarely have the resources we need to keep our data systems running well, and
it's hard to get administrators and funders to see why data systems are important,
because they just seem so mundane.
This is partly because data infrastructure and the work of data infrastructure
maintenance is, by its nature, invisible, even to those that benefit
from it the most.
So, in their book, "Sorting Things Out," information scientists Jeff Bowker and
Susan Star talk about this. They argue that invisibility is
a feature rather than a bug of infrastructure.
Infrastructure is meant to be invisible.
It's meant to be transparent, meaning that it can support use without notice.
The consequence of this, though, is that it only gets noticed when it breaks down.
So think about some of the infrastructures you rely on, on a daily basis.
The roads you drive on, the electric grid.
Most of the time we don't notice these until they break, until the road washes out,
or until there's a power outage or something like that.
For data infrastructures, I've observed that this can make it harder for them to
get funding for ongoing maintenance.
If they are functioning well, no one sees the need to give them money.
If they break down, no one thinks that they're worth paying for.
In other words, the invisibility of infrastructure, data or otherwise, constitutes
a passive threat to its ongoing existence.
However, over the last few years, two years specifically, data
infrastructures in the earth sciences have started facing more active threats.
In the US at least, our databases have become too visible to those who are
interested in defunding science.
These screenshots are from early 2025, and they're taken from the NOAA Notice
of Changes page, which documents edits and deletions of NOAA web
resources.
For the international folks, NOAA stands for the US National Oceanic and
Atmospheric Administration agency, which studies things like
climate change.
So these screenshots are listing over 20 NOAA databases and data resources that
were taken offline following huge budget cuts and layoffs across
multiple US federal agencies in the earth and environmental sciences.
These cuts and takedowns have had a huge impact in the earth science informatics
community. I've lost so many colleagues because of these, half the people that I
used to work with at ESIP just lost their jobs and have had to go
work in the private sector.
And the takedowns of these data resources have led to multiple data rescue and
data resilience efforts. We've been scrambling not just to archive data that we've
spent actual decades collecting and curating, but we're also trying to replace that
human infrastructure and that institutional memory that we lost in these budget
cuts.
So I'm going to talk about three of these data resilience efforts.
Just three, but know that there are many more efforts beyond this.
I've only been directly involved in the first and third of these that I'll talk
about, but not the second. So first I'll discuss some data rescue
work that we're doing at SESR. Second, I'll talk about a project that aims to
identify near future threats to repositories, so the ESIP Repository
Crisis Scorecards project. And finally, I'll briefly talk about a larger effort
aimed at building shared social capacity for infrastructure resilience
led by AGU, the American Geophysical Union.
So starting off with data rescue work that we're doing at SESR.
So SESR, again, the System for Earth and Extraterrestrial Sample
Registration. SESR's been around for almost 20 years,
in its current form.
And it's a giant repository of metadata records describing physical samples, so
things like rock samples, fossils, cores, things like that.
SESR's biggest claim to fame is that it mints persistent identifiers called
IGSNs for samples, which makes them easier to cite or reference in
related publications and datasets.
And we also offer some simple collections and metadata management tools.
So the IGSN is basically a DOI at this point, and there's a long history to that,
and it stands for the International Generic Sample Number.
While SESR's holdings are mostly in the earth sciences, we're currently
undergoing a huge redesign that will make it easier for people in the biodiversity
sciences as well to use us, and I talked about that in the talk on Monday.
I should warn you that if you go to geosamples.org, there's a chance that it will
not be up right now because, like I said, we're finishing up this huge database
revamp.
And, so we're literally finishing that migration this week.
So yeah, it might not be up right now.
So the data rescue project that we've taken on at SESR is of the
IMLGS, which was one of those NOAA data resources that got shut
down in early 2025.
IMLGS stands for the Index to Marine and Lacustrine Geological
Samples. It was basically a giant search portal where people
could find ocean and lake cores to
reuse and subsample. These ocean and lake cores are stored in
core repositories all across the US, and they represent cores from all
across the world. But the IMLGS was the only place you could go
to do a federated search across all of these repositories at one time.
Some of these core records are in SESR
already, but not all of them.
So when the IMLGS portal was taken down,
this
marine and lacustrine community lost a really, really important resource that
helped them do their science and also helped them manage their collections.
So what we're doing at SESR is basically trying to slowly
bring this into SESR's collection.
So bringing all of the cores that are not in SESR into SESR so that people can
search those as well. We're doing this in two phases.
We've already finished the first one.
And the first one was to effectively just redesign the existing
IMLGS repository within SESR as its own
discreet little app, and that's what this second screenshot is of.
Dave Viglase did this work for us, and he did this really excellent job with it.
It uses a file format called GeoParquet that I'm not going to try to explain right
now.
But yeah, so phase one was just literally recreating
IMLGS as it was in January 2025,
within its own little spot on the SESR website.
Our second phase, though, will be integrating all of these records into the SESR
database itself and also doing some slight alterations to SESR's data
architecture and vocabularies so that we better
represent the IMLGS records. There's not a one-to-one crosswalk
between IMLGS and SESR currently, but over the next year, once we're done with
our migration,
we'll start working on this to actually bring those records into SESR.
So that's our data rescue effort, and this is representative of a lot of similar
data rescue efforts across the earth sciences, where people have been trying to
bring shut down databases into still extant databases.
The second resilience project I'll talk about is coming out of ESIP.
So again, ESIP is the earth science version of TADWIG.
So the Repository Crisis Scorecards project came about out of
early conversations in ESIP about how to respond both to the
2025 shutdowns and also to prepare for potential further
shutdowns in the near term.
In short, folks wanted a way of assessing repositories to know what
was at the greatest threat so that they could be a little bit more proactive in
their data rescue efforts.
So this project was started by Joseph Gum,
and it developed a system for analyzing data repositories to better understand
how at risk they are. So this scorecard is basically a Qualtrics
survey at this point, and it's meant to be a tool for self-study for
repositories to go through and systematically assess their potential
weaknesses according to four different crisis scenarios,
including natural disasters, loss of funding, cyber attack, and loss of
personnel. In some ways, this is similar to some existing
audit systems and accreditation systems out of the library
sciences meant to assess the
stability of repositories, but this one is particularly focused on crisis
response and preparedness for crisis response.
So this scorecard project is all available on ESIP's website and in
Zenodo. There's links in the lower left-hand corner that you probably can't
see, but if you Google it, it's relatively easy to find.
And the screenshot that's at the top of this slide is showing some of
the questions that you go through in
answering this survey.
Finally, I want to briefly talk about a project started by the American
Geophysical Union. So this is an infrastructure resilience and
community building initiative funded by the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation.
So this one is an international project.
AGU has brought together repository managers across multiple earth and
environmental science domains and multiple countries and continents.
And starting with this great meeting that we had in Berlin back in
April, AGU basically organized us into task groups
that are developing longer-term roadmaps for data resilience.
So these task groups are tackling a wide range of projects, including things like
business model development and research, so talking about how
repositories can diversify their funding streams and
trying to do some research to understand what people are willing to pay for,
working together to identify shared technical solutions,
and developing things like repository crisis preparedness kits and
building mutual aid networks. So getting repositories to
agree to take on one another's data if the worst
happens and they get shut down without having any additional time to
prepare. So I was a participant in this kickoff meeting, like I mentioned, and it's
my understanding that they would welcome participation from other domains.
So please email me if you're interested in getting in touch with these folks.
So to summarize, these three projects are addressing data infrastructure resilience
across multiple timescales. So CSARS is more immediate, the Crisis Scorecards are
more midterm, and AGU is aiming at a longer-term
resilience efforts.
To close, I'm struck by how all of these projects are about doing
the best we can with what we have,
or preparing to do the best we can with what we have.
Often in standards and infrastructure development, we spend a lot of time talking
about best practices and lamenting about people who don't adhere to them.
But in these crisis response and resilience projects, what we see is that it's more
about doing the best you can at the time and working together in the future.
To quote librarian Trevor Owens, "Digital preservation is about making the best
use of your resources to mitigate the most pressing preservation threats and
risks."
I think this is a really helpful framework, and rather than aiming for
perfection, we're aiming for prioritization and just
really doing the best that we can.
In the future, I'd love for us to talk more about advocacy and activism and how we
can work together to build political will to support our infrastructures in the
future,
and doing things like keeping infrastructure appropriately visible so it gets the
funding that it needs in order to sustain itself.
Thank you very much.
Hi, my name is Andrea Theimer. I'm a professor of information science at the
University of Arizona, where I study-
Thank you.
All right. Shandra, you're up next.
I'll get your talk going here.
Mouse everywhere.
Oh, is that? Yeah.
All right. Okay. Shandra Earl.
Thanks.
Is this... Can you-- Okay, good. Thank you.
All right.
So hi, everyone. My name is Shandra Earl, and I am a biodiversity
informatician with the National Ecological Observatory Network,
or NEON. And today I'm going to talk about our
approaches to long-term resilience, specifically in the context
of data standards and what we lovingly internally call our
hyper-extended specimen.
So for those of you who don't know, NEON is a continental-scale
distributed observatory funded by the United States National Science
Foundation and operated by Battelle.
It is an observatory pointed at the Earth, at the biological systems of the
planet.
It stretches across 20 ecoclimatic domains,
ranging from Alaska to Hawaii and Puerto Rico.
It includes 81 terrestrial and aquatic sites at which open and
fair data and samples are collected according to shared protocols.
The observatory has a planned 30-year lifespan, and we are currently
about seven years in.
A significant strength of NEON's design is the use of multiple
techniques, including automated instruments, airborne
remote sensing, and observational sampling
So automated instruments are going to be your
sensors that we place onto towers or in the ground or in the water,
and they're automatically collecting that data
over time and just sending it to us.
The airborne remote sensing involves planes that we have where we've outfitted
LiDAR
and radar systems onto it, where we fly over each of the sites about every
three to five years to gain that data.
And then observational sampling is going to be your typical in-the-field,
on-the-ground sampling, where folks are either
doing pitfall trapping, they're doing
root cores, they're doing soil sampling.
And so that can involve anything from across the biodiversity
sciences to the geosciences, but it also
includes observational sampling as well, for example, the birds.
NEON collects over 400 terabytes of data
across those three techniques a year, with
650 million sensor readings from those automated instruments per
day, resulting in currently 2.5 petabytes of total
stored data.
With such a diversity of data products and
significant volume of data being generated, there comes many different data
types and file formats as listed here for the NEON
program.
Although not a comprehensive list, these formats and the
standardized metadata supporting them must all be considered in the quest to make
NEON more interoperable and resilient.
So NEON data themselves have been designed and built for
connection and resilience since the infrastructure design almost two decades
ago.
For example, NEON has implemented a provenance tracking system,
where structured data files allow the inclusion of provenance information,
which are critical to building confidence in data quality and tracing.
An issue monitoring and resolution system has been
integrated to facilitate an organized and coordinated approach
for reporting problems.
We have modular
processing pipelines,
which allow us to turn raw outputs that we get from the
sensors into those analysis-ready products while providing that
operational monitoring that I was mentioning.
And of course, we have machine-ready formatting,
which means that the data and metadata are formatted for compatibility and
machine access, not just human reading.
Of course, more can always be done to improve the NEON infrastructure, but at
least these have served as the foundational values for data
publishing.
In addition to the data that NEON collects, NEON also yields
approximately 100,000 samples archived every single
year of approximately 65 different sample types,
including a diversity of cryo samples stored in liquid nitrogen,
as well as traditional vouchered specimens.
And there are over 8,000 taxa represented to date in those collections.
Most NEON samples are curated at the NEON Biorepository at Arizona
State University, all of which are available to anyone for further research.
Like the data, the samples and collection pipelines have
also been designed and built for connection and resilience.
So first, all sample data are born and managed
digitally. So we've tried to move away from
any handwritten or human decision in the field as much as possible,
and that includes the local identifiers that we use to track specimens
throughout processing. So for example, in the beginning, sample
IDs were handwritten onto the individual labels in the tubes, and we've
since moved to using bar-coded stickers to do that instead.
Once samples have been accessioned into the collection, they are given permanent
globally unique DOIs,
which means we can use those DOIs in our
specimen use tracking, which allows us to
track downstream use and impact of those samples.
And lastly, data undergo frequent audits and
assessments
to make sure we're making targeted improvements of the data, with the most
recent being data audited for quality with Bob
Mesibov and AI readiness with Raina Jenkins of
ESIP.
And again, those result in those targeted improvements
so we can make sure that we are publishing and mapping our data to the best of our
ability.
This figure captures an example of the
hyper-extended specimen nature of the NEON small
mammal vouchers,
all of which have primary data of the occurrence record, of course,
images of the physical specimen, and tissue samples frozen
directly from that sample.
These are then related to trait data collected from the specimens,
which can then also be linked to molecular and pathogen data that NEON
tests for,
among all of the other spatially temporally coincident data
that NEON collects.
All of which are then connected to an even broader body
of downstream data and scientific understanding.
There's a great power in the hyper-extended specimen, of course, but also
added complexity for both the data providers and users to
leverage those linked data effectively.
So NEON is continually evolving to provide easier discovery
and stronger resilience of both the data and samples
via many kinds of coordinated standards
across the data, with examples listed here across content
standards, so standards about the fields, and metadata
themselves, like EML, Darwin Core, MIXXS,
et cetera.
Vocabularies used within the fields themselves, like definitions defined by
GBIF, the USNPN
Phenotype phases,
ENVO, et cetera.
We also, of course, use persistent identifiers.
Like I discussed, we use the IGSNs that Andrea just
talked about to give DOIs to our samples.
We have DOIs specifically for each of our data sets that
we use. We use ORCIDs, of course, and we use RORs
to define our users' institutions.
NEON is, of course, always seeking input on which tools
or approaches to embrace, as seen in the standards we're considering adding
for each of these things.
So for example, the work of Kate Ingham off at GBIF in working with us
to map NEON data to the Humboldt Extension and the Darwin Core data product, of
course, allows us to consider and test out how these
new standards affect how our data are published and if they are meeting our
user needs.
But of course, much has changed in the past two decades since
all of this infrastructure was built, particularly from a cyber
infrastructure perspective, as well summarized by this screenshot from a
slide from an NSF Office of Advanced Computing webinar in
April that captures the key resources of such disruption
that defines the context in which we all find ourselves.
We have seen an increase of the amount of data collected from continually
changing specialized hardware and accelerators.
Rapid advances in integration of AI into our scientific
applications and workflows means being continually aware of
modern-day changes.
New business models for computing and data infrastructure when
combined with a lack of resources means we also need to focus on
cross-agency initiatives, global competition, and the need to broaden
access to those resources.
More recently, we see NEON data and samples being used in fields
beyond geo and biodiversity,
as these examples highlight, with the example on the left being a
collaboration with Alaska's Berries Futures Project
to assess food security trends
using NEON phenology data, and the example on the right showing how
NEON groundwater infrastructure measuring nitrate levels was used in
Puerto Rico to determine if well water was safe for drinking after
Hurricane Maria.
Here on the left, we see an example of a collaboration with the US
Department of Defense to take permafrost core
samples from NEON sites in Alaska and sequence them for
potential pathogenic bacteria and viruses to understand
risks in the light of climate change, and on the right, an example of NEON
data being used for AI models at the global scale,
specifically Satellogic's sharing of a benchmark data
set that includes NEON LiDAR data for training AI models.
And I will share some parting thoughts to close, questions for you all to ponder
and hopefully discuss in the discussion portion of this session, and
also to continue the conversation with NEON and the other
participants represented here.
So sharing data improves discovery and use, but how can we
ensure appropriate citation and ability to trace impact?
Standards improve interoperability, of course, but who sustains the
standards? Who sustains the mappings?
Who sustains the crosswalks as data and technologies evolve?
Providing large data sets is great for research, but it's not always
sustainable. So how do we encourage support from large or commercial
entities who use the data?
And how do we
enhance discoverability and connectivity of downstream value-added data
by users?
This is described as round-tripping of the data.
These questions require community-level engagement and solutioning, so we
look forward to hearing from all of you.
Thank you.
Next up is our own James Macklin.
I need a microphone thing, so.
Okay. Yeah.
Is that all right?
Yeah.
You want my timer or you have one?
Yes. Oh, yeah.
Whatever you want.
All right. Good morning, everyone.
So we've seen a lot of high-level overview types
of discussions here. I'm going to dig in a little bit based on a
project, talk about some lessons learned.
I'm going to talk about resilience of data and the ability,
especially in a large project, the ability to synthesize
data from many other places in order to achieve.
And this is going to be done in an environmental genomics perspective.
So, climate change, we all know this.
Substitute your own country and your own pain of the future.
And what are the consequences to the biodiversity in your countries?
We have a large project focused on this.
We're coming to the end, so the lessons learned are being thrown in here.
And this involves many departments in the federal government, which
usually don't work together. This project is specifically designed to
make us work together, based on our own mandates and strengths and
research, but also collaborating with lots of universities,
infrastructures, and global partners.
So it's a very large project looking at using genomics to assess,
predict, and adapt to climate change.
Our approach spans three questions, which you see there, but the
work is really in the quantifying that genetic diversity
using spatial-temporal samples and looking
across to predict that future based on resources like the
climate data.
So one of the things, just going into the big picture for a second, how much data
do we really have that's already accessible to us?
And the answer is a lot, and that is changing
rapidly. So this paper is a little bit older
now, but if you do the ramping up of the doubling,
you see that we're at at least 70 peta.
It's got to be more than that,
to be honest. But the part, the focus on is the environmental
metagenomics data. So most of this data is health data and crop data,
but when you take the slice out of the environmental metagenomics data, not only do
you see that it's increasing rapidly, but
you see that we're going to have to deal with that in some way
as we go.
When you look at that slice, just that environmental data, it's very diverse.
So it's, of course, what you would expect.
It's taxonomically diverse, it's spatially diverse.
It's diverse in the sense of what are they full genomes?
Are they parts of genomes? What markers are expressed? Et cetera.
So lots of diversity there.
When you switch into the context of a country, for us, like
probably many of you, we're slowly doing big projects that are
accumulating. This is genome level,
0.5% of the 80,000 species we have.
And of course, those are focused on economically, culturally important
species, usually the big ones,
because that's where the money comes from.
But the real questions we're looking at in retrospect here is
about fair metadata associated with the sequences, and I think you'll see
that there we have some issues. And then that translation from, ooh, this is
genomics, into something that deciders can use,
which is fairly new to them, this kind of data, for policy,
conservation action, et cetera.
So our project, called GenArc,
is going to add about 20,000 whole genomes, so that's a lot, a
significant contribution, but really across only 30
terrestrial, marine, and freshwater species because we're doing a lot of genomes as
a population-level study to look at that change of climate.
To do that, we have samples from across the country, but of course,
we could not afford or have the time to do this ourselves.
So this is coming mostly from access to samples
and specimens that already exist.
So we are doing MTAs and we're looking for gaps.
So we're filling some of the gaps, but we really are leveraging stuff that's
already available to us.
We've heard a bunch about this. Everybody has their iceberg.
You need your infrastructure at the bottom, your hardware, et cetera.
You move into your software layer that you have to maintain, and that's constantly
changing. You have the genomics data sets you're either borrowing or
generating yourself. Then you have climate and environmental data
coming from all kinds of different sources that you have to take in,
standardize, make interoperable in order to make sure that when you have
results, they're comparable. And we really stress this in this project.
You have your results going into standard publications, but then you have, where
does your data live when you're done?
So who are those repositories that you trust, and how is that
translated into policy? That stack is critical to us.
And one piece that's really important in the sense of that
interoperability, fair, et cetera, is to manage the data
from the beginning in a way that this is accessible.
We're fortunate to have a
research data management infrastructure that we call DINA that allows us
to capture a standard-based metadata snapshot
that is usable, interoperable by default based on those standards,
and can
add value for reusability to the projects that come after us.
So we map several of the standards that this room's very familiar with,
which makes sense in the context of where our focus is on samples.
We do that in a fairly simple and straightforward way.
We try to keep things simple. And we have some flexibility.
As we know, standards evolve. Everybody has their own
terms. Everybody wants their own controlled vocabulary.
So we have these flexible managed attributes that allow, if you can't
map to those standards and you're in the process of generating or just need other
metadata that I've never heard of, you can add it.
When you look at sequences, so in our object store, relating
to-- We use the material sample framework.
You can embed those sequences, so we store them,
and we relate them back to their material
sample data.
I'm going to use a salmon data set, a large salmon data set that we have
here just as an exemplar.
And a point to make here, which I'll show going
forward, is we use this, having the sequences in the object
store plus their metadata. We have workflows, pipelines that we
generate that send this data off to where it needs to be,
which in our case is the European Nucleotide Archive.
Now, this slide is still in DINA. It's ahead of itself,
but I have no other way to really do it instead of making more slides.
When we filtered, so we filtered for those salmon.
How much salmon do we have that have sequences associated?
In this case, we're actually filtering on the ENA sample number because I've
already put it there, but you can do that natively.
And you see that on the map, we have almost
740 genomes of salmon
We have a workflow, again, a pipeline that's fairly new, that pushes that
data in a semi-automatic way. You know that we can't, unfortunately, do it
completely automatically, but this helps researchers a lot, and it motivates them
to actually do it.
We push that data to, in this case, ENA.
Which is great, except for the fact that most of you who work in genomics data
know that these repositories, like the Sequence Read Archive in the
US and the one in Japan, they back each other up, which is awesome,
but they're not very good at metadata.
They only take their core metadata.
You can put whatever you want there, actually, and most of them will allow you to
put more in metadata. The trouble is, is that it's not in any fair way.
It's just there. And if you don't download the dataset, you'll never see it.
You can't search on it. So this is unfortunate.
We're putting pressure on these from the big picture.
We're trying to put pressure on these places, but we don't control them, right?
We're small to them.
So what's the problem here? This is the problem.
This is a great paper. Basically says that we suck at this
and there has to be a better way.
You can see just from this figure here,
I like the way they did this. There's, okay, we have this metadata, which is the
bright green. The gray is definitely missing, and
then the huge bars are maybe outside somewhere.
So maybe the metadata that we actually need is somewhere else.
Great.
And you can see it partitioned the way we like it on this side and those figures.
Yeah, there's really not a lot to go by when you look at these repositories, and
that's unfortunate.
So for us, we have a solution, which is the solution that many of you know,
but is now much more robust in the sense of genomics.
And that is, we have a new workflow that we just finished, which will take that
data, associate the ENA record with rich
metadata in the GBIF infrastructure.
So now you can find it, and you have the links directly to the sequences to
go and do what you need. So this is great.
Thank you, Joe, and others.
Just a few examples here of contributions.
We have many big picture, and of course, we are focused on things like
polar bears and salmon, because that's how you get your funding, you have to
talk about... But we do work on microbiomes and the little guys, I assure you,
in some cases. And it's nice we're at the end of this project and things, sort of
the synthesis is starting to happen. We're starting to see results.
We're starting to actually be able to show, you can see on the polar bear side,
where polar bears are at risk, where their habitats are changing, where we don't
think they'll be able to adapt easily to climate change, pack
ice disappearing, right?
So, one of the things in retrospect for this kind of talk is,
what are we relying on to do our work?
We've seen this a couple times in the talks we've had already, but you see,
here's some of the infrastructures that we rely on for repositories, either
us putting things in or us getting things out.
And you note
in parentheses here, the different sort of ways these things are
funded. And they have various risks.
Interesting, a lot of them are government or government through grants,
but there's great risk throughout this, and we're talking about this.
So, what do we need to do? We need to make sure
that our data is reusable. So unfortunately,
that comes into-- We talked about what's sexy, that's come a couple times here.
This is about researchers. So researchers often prioritize new
sequencing. Ooh, new data. This is fun. Novel analyses.
Let's build new tools. This is all parts of innovative research.
I'm guilty of this myself. And let's publish on what I care about to
give to the people, because that's what's going to keep me employed.
Trouble is, is that that really, the boring stuff of just associating and keeping
the metadata connected to the genomics, actually publishing the metadata at
all in any useful way, that doesn't get high priority.
So we need our researchers to do a little better, and that relates to
these types of things, finding, correcting, and standardizing
metadata. That's so boring. Who wants to do that?
The code, reproducibility, robustness, some of us are really good at that.
Researchers are often relying on others.
They don't really understand it, so they just hope that things are going well
there.
Developing universal reusable pipelines, same deal.
Some are very interested and focused on this.
Others just let others do it, and they don't really know how robust
that is, how resilient it is.
And finally, coming towards the decision-ready part,
we still have a lot of work to do, especially in the genomics world, which is new
and maybe scary, on how to make that data
interpretable, comparable across our projects, and
decision-ready.
And that's it.
And we have a video also.
Yeah.
Easy win.
Brenda is online too.
Oh, awesome. Thank you.
She just got to it.
Cool. Hi, Brenda online.
All right. Thanks, James. And yeah, next up, last up.
So it looks like there are two talks in here. I'm going to play the video.
Is that correct? Yeah. Okay.
Good day, everyone. My name is Fathani Ramwaja from the South
African National Biodiversity Institute.
I will be talking about our efforts to build a sustainable and robust
geodiversity data ecosystem. The South African National
Biodiversity Institute has implemented standardized data
management strategies for South Africa's national
botanical and zoological collections.
The project focuses on transitioning legacy data
into
FAIR, which is Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and
Reusable data sets using globally recognized
informatics standards.
Central to this architecture is the National Biodiversity
Information System, which
integrates data from diverse institutional
partners using standardized software platforms such as
BRMS 8 for botanical records and Specify for
zoological data.
A primary challenge in
national data integration is metadata harmonization,
particularly regarding taxonomic inconsistencies.
To resolve this, SANBI employs the TaxonMatch
algorithm, a fuzzy logic implementation
that matches misspelled or varying species names to
an authoritative taxonomic backbone.
This ensures that data retrieved from the central repository
remains high quality and interoperable regardless of
the contributor's internal interpretations.
SANBI distributes authoritative dictionaries,
including taxa with offers, and
gazetteer data to ensure quality at the point of capture.
The controlled data flow
is designed for scalability and data integrity.
Institutions push new or change data to
staging instances where automated data quality checks are
applied before the records move to the production environment.
This process is supported by extract, transform, load
packages that synchronize data at regular intervals.
The system supports complex geographic data ecosystems
by allowing users to perform spatial searches, such
as drawing
polygons on maps to retrieve species coordinates.
SANBI utilizes the digital extended specimen in
NBIS via persistent identifiers linked
across various repositories. The specimen extends
to species description data, locality information,
collections data, literature and references, common names, and
uses data, as well as images and other media,
which is all highlighted on the NBIS system.
By providing the infrastructure and common standards, SANBI
enables a scalable, unified web portal that
promotes data cleaning, reduces duplication, and harnesses
collective knowledge for environmental monitoring and research.
This system needs to be sustainable,
and SANBI practices a diversified funding model.
SANBI is mandated under the National Environmental
Management Biodiversity Act, which we call NEMBA, to
manage information regarding South Africa's biodiversity as follows.
We must collect, generate, process,
coordinate, and disseminate information about biodiversity and the
sustainable use of indigenous
biological resources and establish and maintain national
databases in this regard.
So having an official mandate facilitates a minimum
flow of fiscal funds, which is under the infrastructure
grant.
However, we are also leveraging external project
grants for functional extensions.
We are also investigating establishing a dedicated
biodiversity information fund to receive, hold, and
transparently disburse non-governmental,
international, and donor funds without financial
year-end clawbacks.
So we need to align the National Biodiversity Information System
with our national priorities. That is explicitly
linking SANBI's information platforms to the National
Biodiversity Economy Strategy, the National
Development Plan, and climate change adaptation priorities,
demonstrating how biodiversity data supports green economy
investment, streamlines EIAs, which is
environmental impact assessments, and reduces regulatory delays.
We need to establish a biodiversity data core
investment consortium that is partnering with
universities, science councils, and South
African national parks to share data hosting, collection,
and maintenance costs while SANBI provides national
coordination, standards, and visibility.
BaDi, which is a project,
provides an example of collaborative platform development
for African wetland and waterbird data.
We need to establish a multisectoral information steering committee,
bringing together government, academia,
NGOs, which is non-government organizations, and the
private sector
to strengthen platform governance,
unlock core funding, share licensing costs,
and leverage in-kind technical expertise.
We need to develop value-added analytics and advisory
services
Keep core biodiversity data openly accessible in line
with the member act,
while offering paid services such as customized data
analysis, spatial modeling, screening
reports, and decision support tools to commercial
users.
We need to adopt a modular cloud-based
architecture and monitoring and
evaluation framework
to maintain scalable
modular systems while avoiding unnecessary administrative
growth and track usage, policy uptake,
environmental impact applications, and decision-making impacts
to demonstrate return on investment and strengthen
treasury and grant funding cases.
Our proposed sustainability roadmap starts
to secure the core funding, which is protect baseline public
funding and statutory functions, then align
with national
priorities,
to link NB's outcomes to biodiversity economy and
NDP, National Development Plan, climate and
environmental impact assessment priorities.
Core investment, create consortium and steering mechanisms for
shared costs and expertise. Diversify,
establish donor fund mechanisms and targeted value-added
services.
Demonstrate value, measure use, policy uptake,
regulatory impact, and return on investment.
And preserve capability, invest in people,
succession, archiving, and resilient infrastructure.
Thank you for the opportunity for presenting this talk.
For more information, please contact Brenda Daly
or me at the
information provided.
Thank you.
Good day, everyone. My name is Fathani Ramage from the South
Africa.
Oh, wonderful. Well, thank you for the talk, Fathani, and hello online.
Before we get into discussion, I want to just make a couple of quick announcements
before I forget. Thank you.
One is, and Javier, please fill in the blanks for me, the
unconference. You sent in a reminder about that.
So look in Whova or what's the-
Yeah, there is a-
... what's the word?
... message in Whova, if you can relay that for online participants. Yes.
And on that message in Whova, they have a link.
You've got the spreadsheet and just pitch ideas.
Okay. There's a link in Whova, pitch ideas. Thank you.
Okay. And, for those of you who are speakers in this session, at the end,
before you leave, please come up for a picture. Okay.
Now,
so we have until 10:30 for discussion and questions and all of that.
Maybe first we could take... Thanks, James.
So James and I will be moderating this part and, maybe
first, if there are any questions for speakers
individually, directly, we could take those and then we'll launch
into
some
other group discussions. So are there any questions for the speakers?
Yeah,
Andre.
Wait for the microphone.
Yeah, please. Yeah, we have folks online, so we'll put you some mic here.
There you go, Andre.
Thanks very much. Andre Zerger from the Atlas of Living Australia.
Ultimately, I will have a question at the end, Jose, for you,
regarding your presentation. I think
that's a really important conversation to start to have
collectively.
I think about where we're based. We're a research
infrastructure in our national research infrastructure system, and
we're one of the few e-research programs.
The remainder of them are mostly capital-intensive, like heavy ion accelerators
and
ships and spectrometers and microscopes.
And the rest of our program tends to operate on a
shared cost model. So nothing's free.
It's subsidized, but not free. And maybe in this
open data space, we're a victim of our success a bit, so it's hard to put the
genie back in the bottle.
But I like the structure you presented towards the end.
But the question is,
have you gone as far as seeing some exemplars in other domains
that are perhaps adjacent to biodiversity informatics,
biodiversity science, where this is working or
where conversations are happening?
Thanks, Andre.
Good luck.
The quick answer is no.
The example that I gave of the
music-related economy is the one I
could find that is quite relatable
because it deals with content information sharing, et cetera.
Yes.
Your question is one that I will
take away with me and maybe next year I can give you good
answers. Sorry, that's the best I can do.
We're in a similar position, and I think we can have that conversation together.
I would welcome that.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Yeah. Any other input on that question or...
Yeah, Joe.
From my seat in the corner here, what are the implications of that?
If you start charging for data at individual institutions,
where does that leave GBIF, the citation tracking ...
is the whole system going to collapse then?
And where's your value proposition of citation tracking if that can happen
federated a thousand places around the world?
So, the argument we're making is that
we're trying to do this at the global scale, and of course, we can't support
everything, but then providing some of that money back into the system.
And by telling countries that are, I probably didn't make this clear,
supporters, countries put in tens of millions of euros into the GEF projects, and
to know that
by supporting GBIF, they're making that investment stronger, too.
So these kind of ideas do take hold.
But I'm really afraid of
the
implications of individual institutions start charging for the data, not sharing it
to GBIF.
The system could collapse, or
you become irrelevant at the global scale because the data's coming in now
is not museums, it's environmental DNA, it's camera traps, it's
automated things.
So,
it's a balance there, and
I certainly won't be advocating for this in my last six months in GBIF, I'll tell
you that.
Can I add something to that?
Just in case my question maybe was misinterpreted,
I completely agree with you, Joe, and I think in the, I'll say,
taxonomy or the classification you showed on your third last slide,
data was one, but there were many other opportunities or pathways, and
I think we're strongly of the view as well that the data's not where you'd go,
but there's products and services.
There are even some of the services and technologies around how we mobilize
data,
the tools.
I think it's entirely appropriate to have that conversation around that, but I
completely agree around the data for the similar reasons.
Yeah. I
think what you said is very true, and it needs to be managed.
I think the point of my presentation is that
we're entering a world where we're going to have a hybrid
type of financial model,
and the fact that you account for it does not
eliminate the path of free data, open
science, and so forth.
You know this from NSF and other organizations, that
you can preserve free access
by using
something that some people call virtual currency or
credits. The supercomputing system in the US
works on the basis of credits, so you can grant
$1,000
of virtual currency
for people who actually are in the
ecosystem of free data providing, free data access, and so forth.
But the reality is that many of the services that we're
going to be needing are going to be provided
commercially.
If you're going to be using LLMs, you're going to pay for it.
So
we can't escape. We can't just be in this
ideal corner where everything is free.
So we have to become a part of the larger system.
And within that larger system, we can preserve open science,
free access, open data provision, but we have to make that
work.
Do you want to respond, Joe?
Yeah. Sorry, I probably got too defensive there.
But the
one thing we've learned in our communications with and in reading the literature is
there are now at least 70 countries who are
talking about some sort of biodiversity credit scheme.
Carbon credits didn't work that well.
Biodiversity credits are all over the place sometimes.
But there is an opportunity there because data has to be managed about the
biodiversity credits. We currently have a
pilot with New Zealand, a very small pilot to
be the data repository. The node is being the data repository through GBIF
infrastructure, and then the change of the
biodiversity in that managed space will be
stored, and the
changing over time will be monitored via a safe
repository of the data. So this is a model that could be used for--
We would like to work with national nodes to be part of the
discussions around biodiversity credits, so the national nodes could be
the data repositories
using GBIF
infrastructure
to facilitate that part of their national planning.
And the biodiversity credit funding within a country is going to be larger
than what your national node is probably getting as well.
Thank you.
Shandra.
Thanks, Jane.
So if I'm remembering correctly, you also asked what are the industries that
we can maybe look to as parallels within our own industry, right?
And so I've actually done a bit of this work in trying to figure
out what other examples we can take and bring into
biodiversity informatics, and the two that I've actually looked into are banking
and medical informatics. So banking's done a really good job of this,
especially when use of standards,
because every single transaction has to be done according
to, and has to have those specific standards.
Okay, so then how do you get banks to use that standard?
Well, they've got certain methods and whatnot, but ultimately, at the end of the
day, that's why you end up paying that 3%.
They have to pay into using those standards, which is why you have to pay that
3% when you ever use your credit card anywhere, right?
And the other big one, again, is the medical informatics community.
And there's a ton of parallels there, but I think the biggest
thing that I've learned in looking at that community versus ours is that the
medical informatics community is a lot more governed.
It is required that they do all of these things that we're talking about.
It is required that their data are fair.
It is required that it is interoperable.
So all of the nodes or all of the little leaves at the end of the tree
have to adhere to all of these rules, versus within
biodiversity informatics, at least in the United States, it's not governed.
There's no mandated, "Hey, your museum data has to be
the same as this museum data in terms of standards, interoperability, and quality."
It doesn't have to be digitized. So that's a big barrier, I think, at least
for us, when I'm looking at that sort of community.
But anyway, I encourage you to look at that community if
you're interested.
Yeah. Oh, in back.
And just to say, this might have already been said a little bit,
thinking about the music industry
standard and thinking about Napster, and I'm dating myself here,
which was basically just a clearing house, and it
would lead you to links,
sometimes sketchy links, to places where you could download music, but there was no
sort of financial transaction. Versus, in the modern
context, we have things like Spotify, where you pay in a subscription
fee, and
Spotify manages those
music resources, and then it pays out
to individual music resource providers,
in a way that is equitable based on the amount of downloads.
Mm-hmm.
And so something like that I think would--
We're going way down a road here. But something like that would be quite powerful
because, I think among other things, there is a vast quantity of
information out there that is not part of things like GBIF because there is huge
capital involved in putting it in, and people are not incentivized to do
that because they don't see a value to them in terms of money
payout. Like, I will get money or some
value after putting my data in because I made my data available.
And I'm also incentivized to do the hard work of metadata provision so
that people can get enough information about the data I provided to
see, "Oh, yes, I'm going to use this." And by getting them to use it, then I get
higher amounts of that payout from the Spotify-type service.
So I think there's a--
I don't know how you do it, but there is a huge untapped
resource in terms of data that exists but is not provided in a standardized way by
simply
monetizing that in a way that
would be useful.
Other thoughts on that? All right, so we could move on to some of our other
questions for other speakers or kind of
general things.
All right, so we've put together-- Oh, yeah. In the back. Yeah, thanks.
Slowly raising my hand in a Canadian way.
Go for it.
So James, you talked about 70 petabytes of data, and that's not
the first time that I've heard of data size as a potential
limitation. And I think Canada, the Digital Research
Alliance, has about 300 petabytes as its total
storage. So there's clearly a wall coming here, and I know that a
lot of the focus is on building compute to drive
AI innovation and stuff, but is there anyone working in the storage
space on building sustainable, effective, large-scale
storage? I don't know who this question's for.
It's Mirella.
Oh, yeah. I get it. Here.
I'm not going to answer the question, but I would say look to the astronomers,
because the astronomers are creating 70 petabytes of
data each month.
So they're the ones who are coming up with the large-scale storage solutions.
And if you go and talk to the astronomers and say, "Could we have this teeny,
tiny, little bit of your storage?" They kind of go, "Hmm, yeah, sure."
Not quite that simply, but
there are communities who are dealing with much, much larger datasets than we are.
Yeah. I would second--
Neither of my mics is working. Okay.
And I would second that. I really think it's a tie.
We've talked about those guys for ages.
And we just still haven't bought into that.
And I think the ganging up is good. We're just a little guy on that side.
Those people, when they are taking in their data,
they eliminate 95% of it. They can't possibly store what they
take in. So they have a research focus. Hopefully, we're not there.
We can still take everything in. But
we will need to partner, and I think that's the key.
Jose, I think you were advocating, in essence, a
market-driven economy where the market could be
subsidized in some cases, or it's direct end users.
But the problem I see with that is that
infrastructure
isn't always funded by a market-driven economy, and
what we're talking about is science infrastructure.
What we're going to be seeing in the US, Andrea's talk about
the Trump administration defunding all of this stuff because they
don't believe in climate change.
What is the impact of infrastructure that
gets defunded?
Well, the market-driven approach is there's going to be a
disaster
some years down the road
You can look at other kinds of infrastructure with water systems, power
systems, road systems.
Governments invest in those infrastructures
in order to sustain
a way of life, an economy, whatever you want to call it.
And I think
what science has been doing since
basically World War II in the US,
has been providing
information, advances in technology,
all the rest of it that has provided a way of life, in essence.
And
I'm not sure how it's governed.
It's been governed maybe through some kind of
peer review,
but the benefits are not individual users
that pay for those benefits.
It's a complicated system.
I'd really like to see a clever economist
describe
appropriate measures or appropriate mechanisms of
governance for infrastructure.
Jose.
I agree with you, and I'm no economist, so I'm not going to be able
to
provide the answer. I think my
main point is that if we design cyberinfrastructure,
we need to anticipate the need to
coexist with an economy of some sort.
So we can't design cyberinfrastructure in a way that is
decoupled
from sustainability and financial issues.
And what happens, and I've gone through that, is that
you create a cyberinfrastructure, say, funded by taxpayer
money through NSF or other institution, and then you're
asked to make it sustainable.
And when you're asked to make it sustainable, your infrastructure is
completely unprepared to function in
some sort of an economic
framework. And so,
the distributed infrastructure is going to include
the big providers and the small providers.
It's a very diverse ecosystem. And if you don't provide
to those providers the tools for them to be
integrated, they're going to have a really hard time surviving.
And if you look at the history of this community, you've had very
good work disappear,
and essentially,
you have folks rediscovering what other folks have done in the past, and
there's no continuity to a lot of very good
tools that were developed
and then disappear. So I think
as a community, we need to start thinking about
some backbone where we can plug and play
with different tools, different services, and
make it all sustainable by design rather than as an
afterthought.
So the counterpoint to capitalism is regulation,
incentivizing companies to do the right thing.
So in the private sector sphere, there are two countries which are exemplary in
their private sector
sharing data with GBIF, and that's Colombia and France, because they are
required to by their governments.
Other countries, they talk a nice talk, but they aren't sharing data
with GBIF, and then
in order to get rid of that nuisance,
paying someone to publish that data is an opportunity
for support of
the system. So regulation is part of the answer here as well.
Shandra, are you still-
No way I'd also say that.
Oh,
I was just going to say, in my small little sphere of Neonasc,
I know we've
moved to an infrastructure from being like all of our data are on physical
servers to moving into the cloud. So we've partnered with Google, so all of our
data just go to Google, which I think, at least now that I'm
thinking about it, raises a different point in that I think scientists
do this fun thing where we try to have our hands in everything, and we're
trying to do the infrastructure. We're trying to do whatever, all the
economic. We're trying to do it all,
when what Jose was saying, I think is really important, like we need to give up
some of those things to people. So all of our servers and all of our stuff are
managed by IT folks who know nothing about what our data are or
how it works necessarily, which can be a good thing and a bad thing, I guess.
But on some parts, it's nice because I don't have to worry about any of that
versus, I've definitely worked for other institutions where I do have to worry
about that, and it's exhausting. So...
Thank you.
All right. Any other general questions, or we could hop into some of our group ones
here.
Oh, Deb, yeah.
All right.
So I'm aware there have been some of this, but I think we could benefit
from more like
what Jose alluded to here. How many people in the room are economists?
How many people are marketing and communication specialists in this room that can
help us reach
These different groups. And
GBIF has an interesting role in that they have sat down with many of these
communities at various meetings, but how can we make sure we invite them
to these conversations in these spaces, so we're not projecting
what we think we need in that space, but they can be collaborators in
helping us figure that out. I,
for one, in my own personal experience then had an experience where I
discovered in the process of writing a paper that there was something called the
Vector-Borne Disease
Project in the US. I had no idea it existed.
But here we were studying pathogen preparedness for collections and how
they can be useful,
but there were no collections people in that vector-borne disease
network at all. There was the call for more
taxonomists to work locally in their own communities, but there
was no connection there.
So I think,
in my experience
in our community,
the social scientists, for example, telling us how we can collaborate.
The only group I know that collaborates with them regularly is the Island
Biogeographers. They invite social scientists to all of their meetings.
They have a track with them present there to negotiate
these kinds of conversations.
Thanks, Deb. And I think the sound of clinking coffee cups out
there is our sign to start to wrap this up.
I want to give a big thank you to the speakers and to ask you not to run away just
yet. We need a quick picture. Thank you all for attending, and
I want to draw your attention to this QR code.
If these are discussions you like to have and topics you're interested in,
these and others that affect us
globally,
consider joining our international partners for the Digital Extended Specimen
group. We meet monthly, and we are
not just discussing things, but hoping to advance some of these points in a way
that works for all of us. So, there's a place to
sign up if you visit this QR code. There's also a place to answer these questions
or to just put any other ideas you have just as a place for us to, like I said,
we're going to be compiling all this into
some kind of synthesized summary kind of a thing.
So if you have ideas, questions, anything, feel free to visit that
document and add that. And, with that, anything
else? Yeah. All right. Well, thanks very much, James. Yeah. Thanks, guys.
Thanks, everybody.
Hi.
First, thank you for having me here.
I'm here today to talk about
the work that we've been doing on the scope of a project, AEGIS, where
we have been
working a bit on standards and implementations for
FAIR ancient environmental DNA data.
So the AEGIS project,
which is an acronym for Ancient
Environmental Genomics Initiative for Sustainability
Is a seven-year program that's investigating
how the adaptive records that are stored in ancient
DNA, environmental DNA, can be coupled
with other biomolecular approaches and support the
understanding of the ecosystem resilience and sustainable food
production.
So what you can see here is a little bit of the framework
behind the project, where they try to collect ancient DNA
samples, analyze these samples across time and space,
understand their adaptative, their functioning, and
understand their resilience into ecosystem change, and then try
to apply that and translate that information
into modern crops and agricultural systems,
trying to produce sustainable food production while also
preserving biodiversity under climate change scenarios.
So in this slide now on the
right,
you can see the data engine of the project.
I'm not going to go into a lot of detail within this data engine.
You can see the data collection and the relation with the ethics and
all of the legal aspects around that, the different analysis
that they do in terms of metadata, sediment
description, lipids,
isotopes, geochemistry, and then all of the
aDNA and eDNA associated work and sequencing,
and also the technical developments associated with it, the bioinformatic
analysis. And then all comes up
into the data storage release and sharing, which is the part that I'm going to talk
about now, that then allows the reusage and the
application into the crop translation.
And
what we're trying to accomplish also in this project is to have all of this
data fair.
So focusing on the part of the eDNA or the
DNA derived data, this project has two main
areas.
Because for understanding what's in the environmental DNA, we need to have a good
reference data set. So we're building reference genomes that will help
us understand what's going on in the past, and these
reference genomes are being picked up from organisms and from the environment.
This metadata associated with these reference genomes, it's
all a machine already, so we have the standards.
This is backed up by the EBP project,
and the Earth BioGenome Project. So the data goes into the
public archives and then goes into the AEGIS data portal, where you
can look for the information that is available.
Then we have the part on the ancient environmental DNA.
For example, what comes from lake sediment cores, and this is where
I'm going to focus today.
In terms of
the main aspects of these ancient environmental
DNA, we have the bio sample metadata.
So we have the information on the context of the sample
and what the sample's about, from where, from when.
And then we have the sequencing data that also includes the
associated metadata on the experiments.
So in general, the idea is that this data will flow into
ENA. So ENA, if
you're not aware of, it's the European Nucleotide Archive.
We are part of the international nucleotide sequence database
collaboration together with NCBI and the DNA database of
Japan.
So the data will flow into there and become public, and also
other
analysis platforms like, for example, Magnify, which is a metagenomics
analysis platforms from EDI, can also pick up the data, contribute to
analysis, and then this will all flow back into the AEGIS data portal.
In terms of the ancient DNA pipeline within the project AEGIS, we can
find here a little bit more detail going from the field core collection
to the archiving to the
laboratory work, and then to the sequencing.
And we can see on the boxes below the type of
metadata that is collected. This is just a few examples that are
collected in different stages. And this metadata
then maps to the data model that we have at ENA.
So I'm not sure if you're all familiar with the data model, but there's the bio
sample, there's the overarching project, and then there's the
experiment, which is the metadata, and the run, which is the actual data, the
sequencing data. So we can see how all of this information that is being
collected maps, and some information is general and transversal to
all other data types, but some information is more ancient
DNA specific as the age estimate, the environmental
context, for example, from the past.
When we started this work, we tried to accommodate and tried to look for whatever
is already being developed and what standards exist.
And the MIAS community, which is the Minimum Information
about Ancient Sequences, has been existing for a
while, and they had been starting to work with Genomic Standard
Consortium to push these metadata standards into the
MIxS
standards.
So when we started the work, we started by mapping the initial mapping
that I just showed, where you can see the AEGIS metadata being
collected to the ENA, and then mapping also with the MIAS
standards to try to,
by these mappings, try to reach a consensus and
help push this back into the standards community.
In these mappings, we also took into consideration and interacted with the
FAIRi project, which is an eDNA community that
are also trying to push eDNA standards in collaboration with the
Genomic Standards Consortium and as a TWG working group.
So we did all these mappings, we had all these discussions, and in the end,
we created an eDNA, ancient DNA checklist.
And this was created because the MIAS standards were still in
discussion with the Genomic Standards Consortium, and we did not have an
international standard approved for ancient DNA.
So
this checklist has 48 attributes.
13 of these are mandatory and try to follow with the
requirements from the community.
And then 17 of these
terms are checklist specific
and they include mostly ancient
DNA specific
aspects as the sample age inference description, the
method, the age,
and
things also relevant as the past broad
scale and local environmental context.
The MIxS already collect the current day environmental context, and
they thought it was very important also to collect the past because the
environment changed a lot since the ancient times until now.
And this is just a
representation of the AEGIS internal pipeline, and this is being
managed by the
Copenhagen University, where they collect and upload metadata
internally. They have their validation
processes, and then they extract the information from the
information they collect internally into the ENA, map it to the ENA
checklist, do their own validation, and then broker the data into ENA.
And here's an example of a very rich
bio-sample that has already been submitted and made
public of one of the samples being used in the project, where you can see
a lot of these
specific ancient DNA information available.
What happened in the meantime
after we've started this process was that the MINAS
extension was incorporated into GSC, into the MIxS standards
in the version seven that was just made public in the summer.
And now we are in the process at the ENA to implement these
ancient DNA checklist according to the MINAS.
So we will transition from the ancient ENA, ancient DNA
checklist into the MIxS ancient
checklist.
So this was all about the bio-samples, but we have been also doing some work around
experiment metadata standards, and this is being done together
with the Global Alliance for Genomics Health Consortium, where
they have developed an
experiments metadata checklist.
They now have a core checklist that focus on the properties that are
common to all sequencing experiments, and we're now
exploring implementation, and they're focusing now on
what additional information is needed for
different types of sequencing experiments.
For example, metabarcoding,
metagenomics, all these different types that will need specific
information. These core checklist maps
very well into the INSDC
experiment metadata standards, so to our mandatory fields,
which is very good because it means that
it's almost there.
And now we're looking into the data. I know I need to finish. I'm almost finishing.
And here's an example also of the ancient DNA
metadata associated to the experiment, where they've already included
some additional metadata trying to accommodate from the
information they're collecting and making it available towards the users.
So to sum up,
these community-driven ancient DNA metadata standards were
developed, and they were formally incorporated into GSC.
So this was a community effort. The metadata mappings that we did
were essential to support these developments and the rich
metadata sharing that we are aiming for.
These machine readable and interoperable standards can support
scalable reuse of ancient DNA data, and
hopefully will be contributing to long term integration of these
paleogenomics resources into the wider biodiversity and environmental
data ecosystems. What I did not mention here
is how this data will or may flow into GBIF
as occurrence data. And that is also something that we
are working on. GBIF already takes data from ENA.
There's already sequenced data being pushed
into GBIF, and
this in principle will
also flow there.
And thank you very much. You have some links there
into the different resources. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Joana. Any questions from the floor? We've got... Yes.
Microphone.
Thank you for a very interesting talk.
I was going to ask
what
you
were thinking of in terms of connection to GBIF, but then you just addressed
that in the end. I also have a question
regarding the user feedback. Do
you already have user feedbacks on your templates and
on the amount of mandatory metadata fields that they have
to provide?
This data has been released quite recently.
We do have other users already using the checklist.
So in addition to the AEGIS dataset, we have other datasets that are already using
the ancient DNA checklist, which is quite promising.
And I guess we were from the beginning into discussion at least
with part of the community that was involved in those standards
developments. But we would welcome feedback.
And I guess within the next few months, we'll now be implementing
what actually went into GSC, which has some minor
differences that we need to tackle.
But it would be good to have some user feedback and to see
how much this is used by the community in the future.
One more question from Piotr.
Thank you. Very basic, simple question from the classical
taxonomy point of view. Have you managed to
identify, or what level of taxonomic
accuracy have you achieved in the
methods? How many species have you discovered, or what
level, maybe some genera or
higher level ranks?
Yeah. So that's a big part of what they're developing in terms of the
bioinformatics pipelines that they're using in the project.
I think there is some species identification.
There is a lot at the higher levels, so genera,
families.
And there's a lot of things that you can't actually identify because
you don't have reference for it or because they're too
fragmented to provide an identification.
So,
that is part of what's being worked on in the project, and with the
purpose of improving the way that this data is identified.
And what is also under discussion is then how will this data
be archived, so these identifications associated with these data
sets.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
That's great timing.
Ah, should I-
If you join me in thanking Joanna.
Should I...
I think we'll be okay.
We now go to a sequence of four virtual presenters.
I know two of them are online.
They are welcome to, or anyone's welcome to ask questions into either the
chat or into the conference app.
And I believe they're coming in via Zoom as well.
Should I press play?
I think that's it.
That is the start of it, is it? Yes, it is.
I think so.
Correct. Yes, please.
Good morning, everyone. Thanks for the opportunity to be with you today and share
our research
about the concept of absence in biodiversity data
collection and modeling.
What I'll present today is the result of a working group
effort headed up by Abby Benson,
when she was with the USGS,
Ruben Perez from the
GBIF, data manager for Spain, Deborah
Arlott from the Swedish Land Grant
University,
Yi Ming from
the Institute of Natural Sciences in Belgium,
Wesley Hochachka from
the Cornell Laboratory of Ornithology, and I'm at the
University of Massachusetts in Boston.
There's confusing language
associated with the absence
term in biodiversity
data modeling, and you can see that from all these terms
that you find in the literature.
There's just lots of them.
And
it was this kind of uncertainty that dominated early
discussions.
What was absence? What did it mean? How to think about it.
And so today, I'm going to
try to recover some of those discussions and thoughts.
I want to start here with
the common use of presence and absence
in everyday language.
And that means, often you're describing whether someone or something
is at a particular place. Were you present at the game,
for instance?
Was your iPhone left
upstairs in your room? That kind of idea.
Would it be present if we look there, or is it absent?
For me,
the
first usage of it was probably in elementary and middle school, where teachers took
attendance by calling the roll.
Students were expected to answer, "Here," or, "Present." Those who did not answer
were recorded as absent.
But
failing to answer did not necessarily mean that a student was absent.
The student might
have been present but not heard or noticed.
And this is the situation, except much more complicated in biodiversity.
Organisms are even less cooperative during biodiversity surveys.
They may remain quiet, hide, be cryptic, or
be otherwise temporarily unavailable for detection.
And so it leads you to think about what's going on here, and initial
thought was
that presence and absence is two sides of the same
coin. It's a pair.
But it's not. It's really asymmetric,
and that's because
presence is a fact, while absence is a question.
It seems unbounded. It doesn't seem like there's really an answer.
And for instance, a missing data point, a null value, is inherently
ill-defined. Did the sensor break? Did the event not occur?
Was the datum simply not recorded?
In data analysis, we have the recent concept of expectation
frames. This is from a new paper. But it's something that
we understood before. It just hasn't been written about to my knowledge.
We quote from the paper, "Absence is meaningful only against a model
of what should have been present. It is not a signal on
its own, but a deviation from expectation."
And so in ecological surveys, that expectation frame is
set by having a survey target.
And you can see the Darwin Core management conceptual
model, and then an absence is no longer unbounded,
and its meaning
as an undetected target can be assigned a zero count.
And here's what the Humboldt Core extension says about
that.
We have defined a survey target,
and its scope is one or more scopes that
describe a target for the occurrences.
It could be something like all the bird species, all the bird species except
some gulls and kittiwakes. It could be
whatever you define.
There are two salmon species in that last line
there.
One of my early ideas was that perhaps books about
survey methodology would be helpful.
Here are a list of books that I looked at
and searched
by looking in the appendix and looking for presence and absence and
detection and related terms. Or later, I got electronic
versions and looked
using the computer. And
generally speaking, these books had great information
about survey design, taxonomic-specific techniques, and
statistical considerations. But generally,
they weren't thinking about the data the same way
we do
as data managers and as people interested in
sharing data.
They were very uneven. They had very different
foci.
They're very highly cited books. In the end,
the
most useful one I found was down here by
Hill et al., called "A Handbook of Biodiversity Survey
Methods," in which there was some
very general thinking. One chapter had a lot about detection,
and then there was chapters by taxa that had different ideas
about what was going on.
So,
I'm not sure if this kind of data will make it in the final
paper, but it made us keep thinking.
The next thing to do was to look at books about the
analysis of biodiversity data. And here,
an important
differentiating perspective emerged,
and that is the difference between data coming from the museum
community and people analyzing that data, or data coming from
a biological survey community.
The data from a museum community is presence-only data plus
environmental data,
whereas the biological survey community had
a standard survey with
the scope of that survey well-defined, and
they had repeated surveys. And from that, all kinds of things
emerge. You have effort, and you can start to talk
about
detectability,
which is the key concept that
has helped clarify what's going on.
These two communities use different modeling techniques.
The museum community used Bioclim originally, and then GARP, and then
MaxEnt, whereas the
biological survey community use
standard population approaches, occupancy, habitat, and
hierarchical models.
And the results were
somewhat different. Museum community had niche models.
They looked at range maps and range extensions and habitat usage,
whereas the biological survey community was doing
abundance estimates in addition, and looking
at trends and habitat use. So they were taking
slightly different
goals.
The biological survey community is very interested in
management. They grew out of that kind of tradition.
And there are different references.
Here's just three
books on each side, which have been important in organizing
how people think about these things and what the problems are with the two
approaches and the two kinds of data.
And
most of you have probably heard of some of these books or know about them.
The methods used can be complex, and software's been
written so people who are not necessarily familiar with those techniques can
use them.
So, what are the results from our efforts?
Well, the
main first result is that the Darwin Core occurrence status
was updated from the terms presence and absence to
detect and undetected.
You have this occurrence status, and here's the result.
This
past May,
the executive committee agreed with
the change from
presence and absence to detected and not detected.
So that was a huge success. That's going to alert
people. All the data managers now will
start be thinking about what that means, and other people will think about what
that means, and that's how we want to record it.
So that's a big
accomplishment. And
a little bit about why this is happening.
There's
a separating of the data collection from the analysis phase,
and we're recommending this new language.
As I said, this presence and absence
describes the underlying biological state, whereas detected and
non-detected describe the observational outcomes.
The biological state is inferred from those outcomes and observation
process, and it's often represented as a probability.
Museum data,
or data from platforms like iNaturalist and PlantNet, are commonly called
presence-only data. We suggest that opportunistic
detection-only data would be more accurate.
Note, a new paper by Abubakar has come out
suggesting using the term detected-only data.
And then for data from standard surveys, we support the suggestion
from Carey and Royle, if that's the correct pronunciation, that detection,
non-detection data would be a more appropriate phrase than the
detection-absence data, because it separates the observation phase
from the inference phase.
And
finally, here's our summary.
We're going to
say that absence
and related terms have been used throughout the
biodiversity literature. That confusion arises for two reasons,
different philosophical perspectives and
two research communities, the museum community and the population biology
community, asking similar questions, but starting with different types of data.
And it's really this idea of detectability that helps us work
through this, what's going on. And that emerged from
mark and recapture studies, from distance sampling, and from repeated observations
using occupancies models.
This is the key concept that
has helped us understand the uses of absence.
So, as I said,
presence and absence are no longer the preferred terms.
It's detected and non-detected, and we're encouraging
the change in language when you describe the kinds of data.
Okay. I'd just like to finish by acknowledging the contributions of the team.
Abby started the absence working group and did a lot of early
synthesis work. Deborah
kept us focused with discussion, emails, and figures.
Reuben brought his enthusiasm for the topic.
Wesley Hocache
for his deep knowledge of ecological sampling and modeling, and
Yiming for making figures and bringing us
our first, and maybe our most important impact by requesting the revision
of the occurrence status term of the Darwin Core.
Thank you very much for your attention today.
Thanks very much, Rob. If it starts, you need to stop it.
I need to stop it. Yes. It
starts
now. I think I'll probably just go to the next...
Let me just see.
Is he online? No. It's just on another
screen.
He wants to come.
Do we have any questions online?
We won't have time because we're butting up to the next,
but maybe we will at the end. And because we're heading to lunch, we can
stay a little bit longer.
Thanks, Rob, also for joining us. I had a look.
I think it's 5:30 in the morning over there where you are.
Did you stop that? Yeah. Thank you.
You just need to click the- Ah, thank you ... button to stop.
My name is Berenice, and I work at CSIRO in Australia.
I am presenting this work on behalf of the team, and this project has been really a
collaborative effort. And today, I will be presenting on work
on marine environmental DNA data publication, and some
preliminary survey findings about where people encounter problems.
So, our main question is: how can we streamline the
process from an eDNA data set to a published reusable data
set?
I would like to start by acknowledging the Ngunnawal people as the traditional
custodians of the land on which I am presenting today,
and I pay my respects to the elders past and present.
Also, I extend that respect to all Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander
people here today.
First, to add a bit of context for this work, CSIRO
operates the Australia's Marine National Facility,
including the research vessel, the RV Investigator, and the
scientific equipment and expertise that support marine research.
But collecting the data is only part of the story.
CSIRO also has a long story of managing and sharing marine data.
Our eDNA work feeds into this bigger picture, and we want to make sure
that the data that we collect today can still be found,
understood, and reused well beyond the original project.
This diagram shows the bigger journey.
From collecting samples and observations at the sea, through managing the
data, to the people who eventually use those results.
For eDNA, it's especially important to keep the links between the
sample, the sequencing information, the metadata, and the
final biodiversity observations.
The ITC where I work, the data center, it helps support that
process by making sure that the information is documented, checked,
and made accessible. So the publication challenge is really
about keeping enough context around the data so that someone else,
whether it's another researcher, a data user, a decision
maker, can understand the data and reuse it later.
So after data is being collected, on the other end of the
workflow, we have OBIS. OBIS is a global
platform that brings marine biodiversity data together in one place.
It makes it openly available. It supports research and
conservation, but it is also a community of people working on
how marine biodiversity data are collected, standardized,
shared, and reused.
So it is not only about storing data, but it is also about
making that data useful for science management and
decision-making.
Here in Australia, we have our own OBIS node, OBIS-AU,
and we work with researchers, data producers, and we
bring the Australian marine biodiversity data into OBIS,
and we make it available broadly. This also includes data from
the Australian Antarctic Program, and it covers a
huge part of the Southern Ocean and the region between Hobart and
Antarctica.
So the current challenge.
Sequencing and bioinformatics are getting faster and more powerful,
but getting the final biodiversity data ready for publication can
still take a lot of work.
To publish to systems like OBIS or GBIF, people often need
to organize the metadata, convert that into the right format, and
check that everything meets their repository requirements.
That means using several different tools, following different standards,
and repeating a lot of manual steps.
So the practical problem behind this project is understanding
where people get stuck
and where better tools or support could make it easier to
turn eDNA results into data that are findable,
accessible, interoperable, and reusable.
And here, this is an example from us, the OBIS
Australia team. Here we show how the challenge
looks like in practice.
On the left, we show the data that comes from different providers.
In the middle,
we show the templates and the tools to help organize the metadata and
transform the data into the right format for publication.
Then on the right, the data moves through the publishing infrastructure
into larger biodiversity platforms.
We already have some tools and building blocks in place, but moving from one
step to the next can still involve a lot of coordination,
decisions, and technical knowledge.
So
we wanted to hear directly from people from the community, where are people
getting stuck, and what kinds of improvements would make the
biggest difference to their work? So we ran a survey.
We designed the survey around five main areas, including
stakeholders and governance, metadata and
standards, technologies and infrastructure, workflow
management, and capacity building.
And we wanted to hear from people across the whole publication process,
including researchers, data managers, software
developers, bioinformaticians, and decision-makers.
And here I am presenting some of the preliminary findings.
So we identified from the survey that the biggest
challenge that people reported was about data formatting.
About 71% of participants selected this issue.
This was followed by two closely related issues, both around
58%.
The issues were differences in standards or protocols and
differences in metadata formats across repositories.
People also mentioned the issue of collecting metadata from different sources
and keeping that information consistent through projects.
That was quite time-consuming. So if we put all
together, the message is clear. Most of the problems
happen when people are trying to prepare and adapt their data for
publication.
And for this audience,
the standards connection is especially important.
It is not only about having standards in place,
as people also need practical guidance and tools that help
them apply those standards consistently across systems and
repositories.
Also, for the second part of the survey, we also have the
agreement questions that gave us another way to look at people's experience
with the publication process.
Around 74% agreed that the publication involves too
much manual effort.
Almost half disagreed that the quality control procedures are
clearly defined. So this does not mean that the data themselves
are poor quality, but it means that people are not always
clear about what the QC process
should be.
So only about 27%
felt that the publication steps were clear and manageable,
and around 36% felt that the technical support was
available when they needed it.
Overall, the pattern suggests a mix of manual work,
uncertainty about procedures, and a need for more support.
So improving the publication is not only a
technical problem, but it's also about giving people
clearer guidance and making the process easier to follow.
Similarly, in our survey, we also asked
people what kind of solutions would make the process easier for them.
The most popular
options were having a web portal to help them prepare,
validate, and submit data sets.
The second one was having an automated submission to the public
repositories,
NCBI, GBIF, OBIS.
The third one was about having automated metadata checks,
and also the last one was about having better interoperability
between repositories.
From these preliminary results, we
see three main priorities. The first one
is that we need to reduce the amount of manual work involving preparing
metadata and submitting data.
Secondly, we need better metadata validation and clearer
guidance on repository requirements so people can identify
problems early and know how to fix them before submission.
Third, we need to test interoperable workflow components
with the people who actually use the tools and make sure that the tool
is fit for real publication practices.
So the main message for this talk is that making
marine eDNA data fair is not only about the technology, but
it is also about making the publication process clear,
practical, and manageable for the people who are doing the work.
Finally,
the survey is still open, and we would like to hear the input from
this community.
If you work with eDNA data, whether you prepare the data, you
manage it, you publish it, we would love to hear from your experience,
including the challenges, what you like, what you don't like, what is working for
you, any complaints.
We would like to hear
what works for you as well, and you can access the survey using the
QR code available on the screen. It takes about 15
minutes,
and yeah, pretty much you can provide your feedback, and you can help us to
refine the priorities for our project.
And lastly,
I would like to thank all of my co-authors, all
collaborators, and the contributors, and of course, everyone who has
already taken the time to share their experience through the survey.
This work really depends on bringing together perspectives from researchers,
from the data, from the standards, and the publishing infrastructure.
And yeah, thank you very much for listening, and I'm looking forward to hear
your questions and also hearing your comments from
the survey. Thank you very much.
Thank you very much, Berenice, and I apologize I didn't introduce
you at the beginning. I was struggling with the technology.
I don't think Berenice is online that I know of.
She hasn't mentioned it.
No.
She is online.
Oh, she is online. So if there are any questions, we can try and navigate the
technology here.
Oh, maybe there is a question.
No? No.
Okay. Thank you.
I like the survey-based approach to
informing
where we head in this space.
It's easy to progress without that knowledge.
There's been some questions about will there be some time for general discussion,
and we've got one speaker short, so there's actually 15 minutes at the end
before lunch. So, we do have a little bit of time at the end.
I'd like to introduce
someone from our team, actually, Catherine Hall,
that will present on visualizing specimens as event chains on the
Australian Reference Genome Atlas.
And I know Catherine's online as well at a more civilized hour than
Rob has in Massachusetts. So
thank you, Catherine, and presentation starting.
Hello, and thank you for the opportunity to speak at TADWIG this year.
In this talk, I will be sharing with you some of the modeling work that we did as
part of the Australian Reference Genome Atlas project, which concluded
earlier this year.
The Australian Reference Genome Atlas, or ARGA, was the fruit of a
project that was undertaken in partnership between the Atlas of Living Australia,
the Australian BioCommons, and Bioplatforms Australia.
We also partnered with the Australian Research Data Commons.
The platform itself was part of the NCRIS community here in Australia,
providing free collaborative infrastructure for researchers.
ARGA, as we built it, was an index, not a repository,
bringing together complex DNA and genomic data sets from multiple
sources. It united them with their specimen occurrence data,
taxonomy, and other traits.
Genomic data are deposited into repositories using
INSDC standards, but not all of our candidate repositories
use these standards. Sometimes we had to deal with repository-specific
terms as well.
On the biology side of the equation, biodiversity data are shared
using Darwin Core standards, standards that are now routinely used.
Blending these two together was a big task, and to be fair, it's a task that's
getting much easier. Tools like the Darwin Core Data Package do a lot
of the heavy lifting to make the task simpler.
But a complication remains in the formulation of metadata indices,
and that is the singularity of the material entity.
The Darwin Core standard itself is very rich.
It can capture locations, geological context, taxonomy,
specimen occurrences. It even has the new extensions that try to
capture specific single genetic sequences.
But the model is also very flat, with one entity giving rise to one set of
descriptors. As you know, TADWIC has developed an event model to
overcome part of this issue. But when we commenced the AGAR project,
we found that we weren't able to capture all of the nuances we wanted for our
event types, and we also wanted to account for versioning in our
own indexation process.
As we saw in the previous slide, even using events, Darwin
Core works on the individual basis.
One entity produces one block of metadata.
But DNA, or more specifically, genomic data,
doesn't come from an organism. It comes from the amplicon
produced in a lab from a DNA extract derived from a
subsample of a specimen. It doesn't come directly
from the whole organism. It comes from the interpolated material
entity derivatives, each of which can be many.
In the process of generating whole genome data, it's possible that a
single organism may give rise to hundreds of amplicons and
thousands of sequence fragments.
Some of you may have seen this image before, and it shows what we wanted to
model within AGAR as we tried to preserve the chain from
individual through to data packet.
We developed the model to interweave metadata fields across an event arc from
wild state through collection, museum deposition, to subsampling
of tissues. We sought to pass through the chain of events within the
laboratory setting and arrive at the deposition of the data files in a
repository like GenBank or EMBL, or Bioplatforms Australia.
The previous slide represented an ideal, the type of modeling we would've
liked to have implement.
But we were modeling data in the real world, and we also needed to
devise our database, bearing in mind the data or
metadata that we might reasonably be able to acquire.
With that constraint in mind, we created back-end tables to capture metadata
across these events using an organism ID to link the
tables. To implement the model, we coupled an IDF layer
to extract, transform, and load data within a relational core
with a GraphQL access layer. We maintained persistent
identifiers like UUIDs and DOIs for data
sets, and ORCIDs for agents, plus stable specimen or
sample IDs to enable unambiguous linking and
citation.
We also integrated taxonomic directed acyclic graph, or
DAG, to align ALA, Worms, and NCBI
taxonomies without flattening
any of those rank shifts for the identity of the organism.
In this way, our architecture turned static records into traceable
narratives of genomic evidence along event chains, starting from
live state and passing through to derived data products.
This structure allowed us to build rich context-based views, which we then
created using Next.js on the user interface.
Our primary point of entry to the event chain was via the organism table.
Here, we used Darwin Core compatible terms, and we then created a
second table to iterate back to metadata that related to the live state of
the organism in question.
In addition to the unique organism ID, we also created a
unique operation ID to identify the record.
On the collections and registrations tables, which are linked via the organism
ID to the previous tables, and to each other via the collection record
ID, we're disambiguating the field collection event from any
subsequent depositions into formal collections like museums or herbaria
and collecting metadata associated with each of these events.
And here, we are linking our source organism to any tissues
and lab samples. The important thing to note here are
firstly, the catalog ID and organism ID are both recorded.
Often with genomic data sets, not all of the tissues are deposited in
formal collections or derived from formally registered samples.
Here, we can still track their provenance using the organism ID.
And secondly, also note the proliferation of the many IDs.
These nested IDs derive from the laboratory treatments.
Each specimen may have many tissues, and each tissue may have many DNA
extracts, and each extract may resolve to many lab samples.
The modeling we've applied aimed to capture the workflow and
preserve the meaning and relationships between the different entities.
In the final table, we recorded all of the data products that arose from
each lab run. In this way, we created chains from the organism
to the actual genomic data product.
With all of the tables, we could have recorded even more, and these
tables absolutely can be extended with even more and more
metadata, such as the original file creation date
or something else. But what we focused on here in this iteration
was capturing a sufficiency of metadata that a provenance chain
could be reconstructed without preserving endless
details in an attempt to pixelate the data forever and ever and
ever.
Here, I want to demonstrate to you what the source metadata look like.
You can follow the link if you'd like to see how we marked up the metadata for the
original genomic data.
But what you can probably tell is that for every line of metadata, we're
capturing the source for the data and linking the metadata across the
tabs for each of the events.
You can look later on if you would like, but to summarize, there are many
field and tissue samples which relate to many
live individuals. For each of the tissue samples, there are many
derived data which are hyperlinked to their source, along with metadata
attributing each sample or datum to a data custodian who is
identified via their ORCID.
Looking here at just a small extract of the data sheet, what I would especially
like to draw attention to is the fidelity that we've been able to build in.
There are 31 different derived data products from the one specimen,
each linked out to its primary repository location where it can be downloaded,
and each links back to the original sample via a
verifiable chain.
Using simpler modeling, we could have said that sample
ANU-ST67 gave rise to 31
downloadable data products. But that information alone
collapses the context and strips out the meaning.
Via the modeling we implemented, users can now know the tissue type, be
that muscle or kidney. They can also know the molecule that was extracted,
whether it was DNA or RNA. They can know the file type, the data
type, and its purpose, as well as the data custodian, leading to
greater transparency and trust in the data, and moreover,
preservation of the meaning of that data.
Another important thing to note
is that creating this data set was curation-intensive.
Naturally, questions of sustainability would arise.
What I will say here is to invoke what I'm calling the data
seatbelt.
In the vast majority of cases, we do not need our seatbelts when we're driving,
until the day that we do. It's much the same for data.
When sequence data are high quality and their use is straightforward and
conflict-free, the provenance tends not to be questioned.
But when a gene looks odd or the phylogeny resolves with a
taxon in a strange clade, questions of data quality and
provenance become critical. Being able to trace the derived
evidence to these foundational specimens and their tissues, and their
taxon concepts is vital.
An additional feature of the Aga build was the deployment of operations-based,
conflict-free, replicated data types.
Here you can see a screen grab of a data record ingestion within
Aga, showing how each record is atomized by its term, with
each entry receiving an operation ID, which relates to an entity,
and it also preserves the relationship to the version of the data
uploaded.
And we're also recording the action that was performed on the record.
In this way, we have preserved a full history of the database actions that we have
performed.
So to recap the build, we developed a complex model for the provenance of
individual derived data products.
We atomized them, and we ingested them using CM RDT.
Using this model, we were able to model every event that led to the
creation of the data artifact, from living specimen through tissue
sampling and laboratory process, to build a representation of the
data product that reflected its generation in the real world.
Each individual record shows a slice of the full history of any genomic
data file, be that the collection in the field or the extraction of
DNA or RNA, and these slices preserve the semantic
meaning of any particular metadata.
They also allow us to disambiguate, for example, the field collector
from the person who extracted the DNA, and from the custodian of that
published data product, or a DNA sample from its
parent tissue, and also from the live bird, which may still be flying
around the mountains of Tasmania.
Using RDF extraction, transformation, and data loading, we
can build custom ingestion templates and map them readily to Darwin
Core and INSDC standards for interoperability.
And perhaps most importantly for our users and their experience,
leverage these complex data hierarchies to build rich and multifaceted
interfaces that reflect the processes through which the data were
generated.
Here's an example of one of the interfaces that we were able to build.
And using a series of cards, we implemented a
guide or a walk through the events,
creating a narrative arc from live state through collection event and
lab process. We were able to chunk the data into digestible
pieces, displaying data relevant for each step along the provenance chain,
providing context as well as enrichments, such as links out to
agents via ORCIDs or to source publications via DOIs.
The approach that we took with Aga started from the premise not
dissimilar to the comments that were made by Ramona Walls on Monday, and
that context and provenance are vital in data science.
We used our model to preserve the meaning of the source metadata, enhancing
the semantic richness. Each of the records in Aga are not
specimens or even genomes. Each atomized record
represents a snippet of time, showing a slice of the long sausage
that is the journey from live organism to DNA-derived data product.
We sought to reflect the real processes that were involved in the generation of the
data. And though simplified, we preserved sufficient
meaning that we could build flexible narrative interfaces to enable data
exploration. Additionally, we were able to enrich the source
data using interoperable components like ORCIDs and DOIs to knit
these data provenance chains
into other infrastructures, like the corpus of literature or ORCID.
Most importantly perhaps, the data model in Aga allows each record to be
interpreted within its original intended context, generating
trust and allowing users to interact and reuse data
from a secure foundation of understanding its full provenance.
And in conclusion, I would like very much to thank the Aga team for their hard work
in bringing Aga to life, and thank you.
Hello, and thank you for the opportunity-
I'll get the exit for you
... to speak today with you this year.
In this talk, I will be sharing with you some of the modeling work that we-
Thank you
Thanks, Joanna.
Just in the interest of time, because we've got the 15 minutes towards the end, I
think we'll keep going.
Unless there was a question. I'm not seeing any questions.
Laura from INS-
Not yet for this. There was a question online for Rob's
presentation.
And that was our fault, and then he left.
Well, the question he answered, it's not directly towards him, it's actually a
GBIF-OBIS question.
Rob is still online.
Okay, thank you. But are there any questions from the floor?
We'll try and navigate this somehow.
To Catherine, that is specifically, or Bernice?
No. Okay, great. Well, we'll go to our last presentation
and take it from there. So I'd like to introduce Peter Ogheghe.
Morning. I am Peter Ogheghe from the Forest Research Institute of Nigeria.
You don't have much more to say than that, and it's
self-explanatory, so thank you.
Morning. I am Peter Ogheghe from the Forest Research Institute of Nigeria,
and I'm here to present our work
titled, "Bridging Biodiversity Data Standards &
Predictive Ecology:
Operationalizing Interpretable Workflows for Species
Distribution Modeling in West Africa."
And I'm presenting this on behalf of my co-authors,
Emmanuel
and Omo-Akefe.
So the work actually simply asks a simple question.
When standards-informed processing changes
biodiversity occurrence records, does that difference
survive through a species distribution modeling workflow
and ultimately affect what we can infer?
We investigate this using six West African timber
species.
And to answer this question, we distinguish three levels
of effects.
First, record representation. Does
standards-informed processing change the records?
Second is numerical species distribution modeling information.
Does that difference survive common spatial and modeling
preparation? And thirdly, predictive inference.
Does enough of the difference survive to
support a pathway-specific predictive comparison?
The key point is that a difference in records does not
automatically mean a difference in model information.
And so we designed a controlled experiment to follow
the progression.
We started with the same 46,941
occurrence
records for six species.
Pathway A used relatively minimal processing, while pathway B
applied explicit standards-informed fitness-for-use rules.
Everything downstream was then held constant.
The geographic domain, spatial processing, its
predictors, background data, the three algorithms, logistic
regression, random forest, and histogram gradient boosting,
and the validation framework. This allows us to
isolate the effect of occurrence data treatment.
So did that treatment actually change the data?
Yes.
Pathway A retained 46,941 records,
while pathway B retained 46,835,
a difference of 106 records or about
0.23%.
These exclusions included geospatial
placeholders,
cross-dataset duplicates, and one fuzzy record,
plus four absent records. So the first result is clear.
Standards-informed processing produced a measurable
record-level effect.
But
what mattered next was that,
was the spatial information represented by those
differences?
That is what matters next.
After restricting both pathways to the West African modeling
model
domain,
the difference fell to just 70 records.
More importantly,
these records were highly concentrated.
They involved only three species and 16 locations,
with almost
89% occurring at just 10
locations.
Critically,
every A-only coordinate was already represented in
part B
at the same coordinate
or environmental cell.
So although record counts differed, the pathways
increasingly represented the same spatial
information.
So this becomes important after applying the common spatial processing
rule.
Common spatial duplication, the replication, remove
the remaining numerical distinctions between the pathways.
Both produce exactly 36,407 present sampling
units.
With the same 60,000 background records, both
pathways therefore reached the same 96,407
row modeling mattress.
This is the central experimental result.
The upstream standards
effect was real, but it did not survive as distinct
numerical species distribution modeling information.
And that convergence determined what we can legitimately
infer
We can therefore distinguish three conclusions.
At level one, a record and provenance effect was observed.
At level two, distinct numerical
species distribution modeling information was not retained.
Consequently, at level three, a pathway-specific predictive effect
was not identifiable.
We therefore did not fit separate pathways models simply to manufacture a
comparison. Importantly, this does not mean
standards had no effect. It means their upstream
effect did not remain numerically distinct at the modeling stage.
We then evaluate the resulting common modeling information using
geographic validation.
And our primary evaluation used strict geography spatial
cross-validation designed to test
transferability
to held-out areas.
Across the six species, selected model
ROC-AUC ranged from approximately
0.66 to 0.75.
Triplochiton sterozylon achieved the highest spatial
ROC-AUC, while Kayau senegalensis had the
lowest.
The selected models varied between random forest
and histogram gradient boosting, but we make no claim of
statistically significant algorithm superiority.
The importance of geographic validation becomes especially clear when we compare
it with random cross-validation.
The validation comparison produced one of our clearest findings.
For all six species,
random cross-validation gave higher ROC-AUC
than geographic validation.
Mean performance fell from approximately 0.99 under random
validation to 0.70 under geographic holdout,
an average difference of 0.28.
This shows that random validation can give an overly optimistic
picture of model performance when our real interest is geographic
transferability.
We also found that model robustness cannot be
represented by ROC-AUC alone.
We therefore assess robustness across several dimensions
separately.
Triplochiton performed best for spatial discrimination
and stability.
Pterocarpus had the highest precision-recall performance, while
Millettia had the lowest Breyer score.
So no species was strongest across every dimension.
This is why we avoided a composite robustness score and
interpreted discrimination, probabilistic accuracy, and
spatial variability separately.
What then does this experiment tell us about diversity
standards?
I summarize the interpretation in three statements.
Standards govern what
enters the analytical pipeline.
Workflow design governs what information survives it,
and validation design governs what claims can leave it.
In our experiment, standards changed the records.
Common spatial processing determined whether that difference persisted,
and geographic validation determined the strength of the predictive claims
we could make.
This leads us to four take-home
messages.
First,
standards in form processing produce a measurable upstream
effect.
Secondly, that difference did not remain distinct after
common spatial and background processing.
Thirdly, pathway-specific predictive divergence was therefore
not identifiable from distinct
numerical computes. And lastly, random cross-validation
substantially overestimated performance relative to geographic
validation.
Overall, reproducible biodiversity modeling requires us to make
standards, workflow decisions, and validation design
explicit.
And with that, I want to
thank my co-authors, Emmanuel Akinnoye-Amofa and the Forest Research
Institute of Nigeria.
Our final message is simple: reproducible inference
depends on what enters the workflow, what survives it,
and how it is validated. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Peter.
Peter is online as well.
Oh, Peter is online as well. So,
if there are any questions or comments,
I'd welcome them.
And I should thank
the presenters for joining us from afar.
This is not an easy thing to do.
There's one question online there, sort of buried because
some might be in the individual presentations.
Oh, maybe you could ask it, Laura.
Yep. Oh, thank you. There is a question
in the individual presentation chat for
the rethinking absence
presentation, and the question was from Ricardo
Ortiz in Colombia. "Regarding the change in the
suggested vocabulary in the term occurrence status, do you know
if it will change the basic filter in the GBIF data portal and occurrence
status as a mandatory field to publish through OBIS?" I
actually answered from the GBIF perspective, we do have an open
issue
for the portal to get that updated.
So you will see that soon in GBIF.
I don't know about the OPIS side of things.
So I don't know, Rob, if you're online, if you have any information on that?
Can you hear me?
Yes.
I do not have information
at this time.
We're hoping that
people start to
adopt the new terminology, but
that always takes time, and
the
data managers
need to
start to see the recommendation, and then
the cultural change can begin.
Great. Thank you.
Well, if there are no further questions, I'll thank our virtual
presenters, and also thank you very much for attending this session.
Very grateful, and Joanna for being here in person.
Thanks, everyone. Enjoy your lunch.
Thanks, Dag.
Who knows Zenodo?
Who knows Biodiversity? ZPMC?
Who knows
BLAZI?
Okay.
Now we get definitely more. Okay. So
the
symposium is planning the LibraScope, and it will be
kept very informal now that we are a few people.
So if
you have any questions, you should put up your arm and ask questions.
I think that is probably more useful.
It is planned to show
presentations,
explain a little bit where the business roadmap is, where we want to go, where
the LibraScope is, and then
show
based on an exemplar presentations, developments that occur.
How do you move forward?
So the premise again is we don't know what we know.
So there are 500 million pages of printed records, we assume.
There are maybe 2,000 journals publishing taxonomic
data, many more in ecology and biodiversity.
Probably there are about
20 million to 50 million taxonomic treatments.
These parts of a text which are about one taxon.
There are
2.5 million species described, and there are about 10% to 30%
of data about these species accessible.
That means not just have a
reference, but really be able to actually look into the text.
So in 2024, we gathered about 50 people
from Europe, India, some other places in
Decent East, that's a monastery in the Central Alps, to actually think about what
we did over the last 10 years in terms of opening up biodiversity
data in general. So we did a lot. We got
genomic data is open, the specimen data is all open, but literature was
not.
So we
decided to focus on
opening up the scientific literature.
And so the goal by 2035,
that's the business roadmap, is to make the 100% of
all the major biodiversity publications open and fair,
to make it machine actionable formats, to make it fully
AI-ready now, so it can be reused. It can
take over the role it has as trusted data.
And
we hope that the funding comes behind and says we need also the
infrastructure actually support this.
The LibraScope is
the idea behind it that we cannot do everything at once, but we have to actually
focus. So we focus on things we want.
So we have
the entire
business roadmap is use case-driven.
So we say we want to do this,
and then we develop the tools to get all the data, make all the data
accessible. So that's why you see the LibraScope is actually targeting into
this huge realm, huge sea of knowledge, and then
fishing out the data we want to make it really accessible.
The why paper we
want to publish is published as a preprint,
but still, it's
depending on peer review, which takes half a year now or
more. So we don't know yet when it comes out, but it can go to Zenodo
and
the link is in here.
So where are we now?
Actually, we are pretty much advanced.
So we have a lot of data that allows you to do this fantastic thing.
So we can visualize the content in our publications.
You see dashboards are one.
And the nice thing essentially is that GBIF
also supports that. So we have
dashboards now as hosted portals in GBIF.
There are about 30 or so from publications.
We can also create triple source for all the taxonomic names
extract, so you can start building a knowledge graph.
And the really important point about these points on the map we put is that
they all have a provenance. So when you go from this map,
it's not just a map and there's a DOI or so, but actually
can go back to the exact position in the text.
From text, you can go here to
the text, to the encoded text, and it works because each of these
annotations, they have a
persistent identifier. And so essentially can go back to the
literature.
And the way it operates is that we have now an entire workflow that takes
PDFs or XML and extracts all the data.
And once it's quality controlled, it goes into the GBIF.
So
the first part we have is Brian Krug will partially talk
about this, is like, how do you discover all these publications, the huge soup of
millions of publications that come out? So how do you get them?
And then
what we can do is that we can actually take all these publications, we can store
them in Zenodo. That's one way. You can do it many other places.
But in Zenodo, we build up these communities that you can actually collect all the
publications on a specific topic.
And you can also see later why. So for example, here, Taxadros is one
community where all the data about fruit flies is collected, which then
goes further along the line,
and it can be processed, and it's being processed.
And you see the Zenodo itself, the biodiversity literature repository is highly
used. So they're really huge number of downloads,
and it's also very large number of the deposits in Zenodo.
And so we have essentially now entire workflow.
That means in the best case, the publishers publish something in
the afternoon. It's all in GBIF. It's widely disseminated.
So the lag from publishing to being cataloged to get into
the other databases is from couple of years is put
down to less than one day.
And so we have tools to find, we have tools to process, and we have also
partners to actually make use of the data.
And in this talk today, so Gida will talk first
about real-time access. Then Rainer will talk
about the IPBES case, which includes also-- It's not
complete the sequence, but doesn't matter.
And then
Chris will talk about
XML first, create
semantic data at the beginning. Then Patrick will talk about literature
triage, and Rob talks about a use case, making use
of this data.
So and Chris, he talks about this, the
AI-ready data. And also if you go outside, you see this
Orfo,
a new tool which essentially has the same function to actually create
semantic-enhanced data at the beginning.
And so we have also a lot of
data now, trusted data we can use. And can show.
So we have 1.2 million treatments now extracted.
And some things which are interesting.
So over the last 10 years, we processed roughly 200
journals.
And you see it's sort of a line between around 10,000 new
species every year we discover. So it's not increased among these journals
or decreased. So it's sort of an
interesting line, which
is not really going up, it's not going down.
And so this gives us some idea. So number of articles, we process something
under 30,000 articles, and then they move down.
And they move down because there's quality control involved.
So Treatment Bank is sort of the data lake.
And then down there, there are specific
users. They have the specific demands.
So what we can see is that we're pretty much
ahead in the way of the pack, if you want, say, from publishing point of view.
So we have workflows, it's all standards-based.
We have repository, which is really supportive and
long-term.
We have a production, we have trusted data, we have APIs.
We have bi-directional linking. We have feedback loops.
So if something is wrong,
within a very short time, you get feedback.
You can get these things corrected either by yourself or it's being
done. There's training.
And
more than this proof of concept, we have a real-time conversion now on
the setup. So our biodiversity data gets really accessible.
But the problem is, we kind of live in a world where you have a lot of data,
and it goes in a funnel, and then we make sort of a mess, and then we have to go to
extract all the data.
And so there's various issues. The data is not published for
machines, and it's time-consuming, it needs curation, and
so on.
But our problem is that
also there's a huge bias. So most of the biodiversity
world is in small insects, and it's not in what you
normally publish. So we should really also look into how we
can get rid of this bias. That means you also probably should not just focus on
how we get data out of publications, but also how we actually discover
what's out in the world.
Okay. So we recently published a paper, a new
model. It means essentially we need to collect a lot of
data and try to use combination of DNA and
optical data and make sure we actually cover the small, the
unknown, the dark taxa, and then we keep all the data
digital
and enhanced, so that when you actually publish, we get
publications that include all the links, everything you want.
And so you see the ORFO is one
way to do that.
So from my point of view, that's why I say that the future is the future.
I think we need to find a solution that we don't focus really
on old, but really think what can you learn from the old,
and then also build new tools to actually
remove all these shortcomings so we can process much
faster, our data is accessible. And there are
sort of indications that we probably only know 10% of the known insects,
for example. So how we can describe the 90% which are not
known?
And so from that point of view, and the Libroscope then adds to that, that if you
actually find out this is a known species, you should be able to find out all
the data about this, and then also the biotic interactions and so on.
So we should be able to actually dive into the old literature.
Thank you.
So our next speaker is Guido Sauter,
and he will talk about real-time access to data in new taxonomic
publications.
Thank you, Donat, for the introduction, and
also thank you for allocating my talk and
what I will be talking about in the bigger picture.
Next slide works with this thing, I take it? Yeah. Okay.
So
I will detail a little more on this way from what Donat
showed from the PDF into semantic XML, into
HTML, and then into GBIF, and a few other places as well.
So
what does real-time access really mean?
When I got assigned this topic from a computer science perspective, I
was first like, "Real-time? Hmm, we're talking autopilots and driver assistance
systems and something like that."
Got to set the record straight here. This is not what real-time means in this case.
So as Donat mentioned, same day or within a couple of hours.
So what data do we have in a taxonomic publication?
First, of course, there is the original publication, the PDF,
because that is still what we cite and what I tend to think we will
be citing for the
foreseeable time.
But then there is named entities like names, occurrences, specimens, gene
sequences, and then also larger chunks like treatments,
and then figures, and also tables, which are rich in data and
help a lot with analysis and visualization, as we've already heard this
morning.
And
real-time access basically means, of course, within a couple of hours, barring
quality control, because that takes time.
And I will detail a little more on where exactly and which
parts take time. To get citable sub-entities like figures
and tables and put DOIs on those, so you can reference them directly and
say, "Okay, not only this publication, that page," but you can say, "This
figure or this table says the following," to be publicly
accessible in global repositories that are persistent and have a DOI on them.
Basically, it all goes to Zenodo. It all becomes dedicated entities, and
they're all interlinked and linked together, and also linked outbound to
GBIF and all sorts of other places as well.
So how does this process work? Donat gave the big overview.
I'm zooming in a little more.
So the very first thing is we need to
get our hands on the publication. That works in a
few different ways.
From Lubo, who already publishes XML, thankfully,
we pull the RSS feeds and pull in the TaxPub.
That takes a little normalization due to the underlying JATS being very liberal
with regard to paragraph nesting.
So, it's not all in clover just yet
because there is potential structural normalization to do.
With PDF, however, it's a little more involved.
Got to get our hands on PDFs and that largely depends
on publishers.
The MNHN journals, they upload them directly, so
it's a very direct route. Some other routes are a little more
winding, let's say, and
sometimes through a few gray areas to just get the PDF.
And then that gets decoded, afterwards batch processed,
quality controlled, and then
exported, disseminated, and then
some exports obviously yield additional identifiers like
GBIF generates a dataset key.
Zenodo gives us DOIs, et cetera. Those go back into the source
publication and then also get distributed to the other repositories.
So for instance, in Zenodo, you also have the links to GBIF.
And now I'm going to zoom in a little more on the top part of this, mainly.
So
just briefly introduce the intake, TaxPub, a little structure normalization,
PDF intake, and then you have to do document structure detection.
And this point is
what takes up a lion's share
of the effort down here
in the quality control, because that basically means going from a physical
layout that is driven by page boundaries and paragraph breaks and everything
back to semantic layout, to flowing text, normalizing that
structure, because that is the basis for
everything to follow.
Extracting the metadata from the document head,
parsing the bibliography, marking the citations,
extracting the taxonomic names.
Most important, the treatment taxa and the
citations like synonymizations and these things, but
also host plans and things and material citations. We tag all of them.
Then
structuring
a PDF into sections, treatments,
and
the treatments into inner data domains, what's the nomenclature,
reference groups, materials
examined, etymology of new names,
a discussion, comparison to other species,
and so forth.
Then,
the reference groups, we link them to
the cited treatment whenever we can.
That is, if we have it.
We also link
the taxonomic names to Catalogue of Life identifiers
because it's the one reference catalog that's out there.
Do the material citations, parse them out into individual records,
also link accession numbers to ENA
where we can, and then this all goes through quality control.
That would be that part of the batch processing, and that all happens
within the PLAZI infrastructure.
And then
PLAZI infrastructure is the part that's in green here,
and all the others are
the various entities get exported to all sorts of other places.
We have the references bibliographic metadata.
They go to RefBank. I don't know who's heard about that before.
It's
just a repository for naked bibliographic references that we built in
an EU project early
2010s.
From ZooBank, we also do an uplink for new species
or we're trying to do it if there is no ZooBank
LSID given in the publication.
And we also
import on a regular basis other new names that we
don't have the treatments for yet from ZooBank to add a
marker, so-called treatment stub, that there must be a treatment
because that species was just published and
must have been described somewhere.
And then we try to get our hand on the publication proper and get the original
description.
And
we locally extract the tables
because they might be broken up across multiple pages, for instance, and that has
to be accounted for and reassembled.
We extract the treatments, create Darwin Core archives.
Then these things go to Zenodo,
to Biodiversity PMC, to OpenBiodiv, to
CyanoSpecies, which creates an RDF graph of Catalogue of Life and
everything that comes in augmentation from our end.
And also to CBILS and to GBIF and Checklist Bank.
So that's the overall picture.
The reason some of
the right side-
are halfway yellow, halfway blue, is we export data there,
but we also get back identifiers.
So the blue ones are pure exports. The yellow
ones, the bottom left,
are
pure imports.
And these ones are basically exports that
return additional identifiers that also get disseminated.
That's a bit the color-coding here.
And
so the result of this
big
dissemination pipeline is that
we have the PDFs publicly accessible in Zenodo,
where applicable. Others, they are copyrighted, some of them,
so we cannot simply put them out in the open. That's what ResearchGate is for.
Figures and tables are accessible.
Treatments, publicly accessible on Zenodo.
Names and occurrences in GBIF, and everything's linked together.
Existing names linked to Catalogue of Life, so
people can go in and
find the name and find other things about it.
New names linked to ZooBank if possible, and also
synonyms and synospecies and articles in Biodiversity PMC.
New names also available to Checklist Bank.
They don't go instantaneously into Catalogue of Life just yet.
We're working on that.
And everything is interlinked and machine actionable.
So
this is what we do, and
going back a little bit,
the problem about PDFs, again, is mainly the
document structure detection normalization, which is what causes
a good part of the effort in quality control.
So XML
does away with a lot of this effort, thankfully.
Therefore, it's a way faster
way to move forward and a way better way to do semantics
in the future.
Now, I'm happy to take any questions.
Thank you.
And I'm handing over to my
successor. This is how we deal with the past, and now Chris is going to
outline the future and the way forward.
Yeah.
Yes.
And the presenter mode. Yeah.
Perfect. Thank you.
Okay.
Okay, hi there. So I'm going to talk about the biodiversity literature as
FAIR and AI-ready data by design. So over
time, the publishing process has generated a very vast
corpus of taxonomic, biogeographic, and molecular
information. And in recent years, as demonstrated by
Guido, the community has developed increasingly effective
ways to liberate legacy literature.
But the central idea of my talk will be pretty simple.
The next step is not simply to liberate more literature, but it is to
change how we publish it.
So publications are not
simply the final output of biodiversity research.
They are part of the infrastructure through which biodiversity
knowledge is validated, connected, and reused.
A single taxonomic publication can contain
very rich information.
We are talking about taxon, material, sequences, places, people,
et cetera. And these elements are already connected conceptually,
but most of those connections are expressed primarily for human
readers. And the challenge is therefore not to only digitize
publication, it is to make these entities and relationship
explicit and machine actionable.
So some projects such as B-cycle have demonstrated that
biodiversity data can be liberated from publication.
Taxonomic treatment, material citation, and references can be enriched and
connected, and the resulting data can be pushed to
data infrastructures such as Treatment Bank and outward GBIF.
Up to date, as mentioned by Guido just before me, Plazi
liberated more than one million treatment from Legacy.
So the question is no longer whether we can liberate the data.
We can, but should this remain the way we actually publish?
If we continue to publish primarily as PDFs and then
extract data afterwards,
we will continuously create new material that
needs to be mined, then annotated and quality
controlled, and it is very resource-consuming, and
errors can occur. So there is an important
distinction to be made between the legacy issue and the
prospective one. For the legacy extraction remains
pretty variable, but for new research, we can move
the creation of machine-readable structure into the publishing workflow itself.
The objective is therefore not to
replace legacy liberation, but it is to complement it with
a prospective
approach that does not create the same backlog.
So instead of producing a PDF, we can work from a structured source.
In XML-first workflows, the structure of the article is captured
during the production of this article, and the same source can then
generate many outputs
for human and machines, PDF, HTML,
data representations, et cetera.
And the important point is not the XML as a file
format in itself, but it is that the machine-readable structure
exists right from the start. And this is the logic
behind
tools like ARFA, MitoTaxa, and the single source publishing approach.
For example, in MitoTaxa,
we have the manuscript that is structured and converted in XML TI,
then annotated in JATS TaxPub through GoldenGate,
and
then the main file, the pivot file, can be exported
to the outputs I talked about already.
So the first
structural level is metadata, title, authors, journal, and
other bibliographic information.
And this is important because metadata
is what makes the publication discoverable and identifiable
across systems.
We consider it not the administrative
overhead at the end of the process, but it is part of the data
that are being produced.
Also,
the references
are often treated as the bibliography, again, at the end of an article.
But in a machine actionable workflow, they are considered to be a structural
object. A reference can be decomposed into pieces.
Once structured, it can be matched against other records, and when a DOI
is available, a resolve to the referenced object.
And this matters especially in biodiversity knowledge, because references connect
to previous works, previous treatments.
A structured reference can then preserve a relationship that is valuable
for building the knowledge graph.
So however, structure alone is not enough.
A machine can read XML without
necessarily understanding what information means.
And in MitoTaxa, for example, the XML
TI file is annotated in JATS TaxPub
using the PLAZI GoldenGate. For example,
material citation is no longer a paragraph of text.
We can identify a taxon, a specimen, a locality, a
date, a collector, et cetera.
The material citation,
in this way, we can express relationships such as treatment describing a
taxon, a treatment citing a specimen, or a specimen being deposited in a
collection, just in this little paragraph of material
citation. Semantic markup therefore make entities and
relationship pretty explicit. And once these are
explicit, we need a common way of
describing them. And now I'm going to talk about the
grammar of interoperability, because indeed, machine-readable
does not automatically mean interoperable.
And two system can both produce XML and still use different
structure or meanings.
And this is why
standards are essential. For example, JATS TaxPub provides a
structured framework for publishing and annotating taxonomic content within JATS,
and Darwin Core provides a shared vocabulary.
Ontologies
also actually add further shared semantics where needed.
And the important point is that the standards provide a common grammar.
They allow us publishers, but also repository and
biodiversity infrastructure to interpret information consistently.
Standards allow that meaning to travel across system.
But even when two system use the same vocabulary, we still need
to know exactly which entity we mean.
And for that,
we are using PIDs, so persistent identifier, but
you know of it,
help us identify exactly which thing we mean.
For example, a publication can have a DOI, an author,
an ORCID,
a collection, GeoCycle.
This distinction matters because a name written as text is not
necessarily a unique identity.
But PIDs provide stable, resolvable
identities that can be used across a system.
And importantly, in the case of a workflow and
in general, PIDs are not just links.
The value come from being used consistently from a system to another.
So the objective, of course, is not to simply produce a
structured article and a long list of IDs.
The real value appears when precise entities and their relationships are explicit.
A publication can describe a taxon, cite a previous treatment,
cite examined specimen, connect those specimen to collection, connect
authors to institution, et cetera.
But when these relationship are expressed properly, the publication becomes
part of an interoperable knowledge network.
And at this point, we can see that FAIR can be designed
into publishing workflow itself.
Findability comes from rich metadata and PIDs.
Accessibility depends on
open resources and resolvable identifiers.
Interoperability depends on shared standards and
vocabularies, and reusability depend on semantics, provenance,
and also appropriately sensing. It is really important.
The key point is that this property reinforce each other.
They are not separate technical
embellishment, but together they create the condition for fair
reuse.
And
when many publication are produced and connected in this way,
they become part of a wider
biodiversity information ecosystem, what we call the
Libroscope. And semantically enhanced publication
can contribute data to resources such as
treatment bank and connect outward to GBIF collection,
taxonomic
database and sequence database. And the value comes from the network of
connection between this infrastructure.
This is the
broader vision. Publication become active contributor to the
interconnected biodiversity knowledge infrastructure.
And
this leads us to the AI-ready topic.
So AI-ready does not simply mean that an AI can
ingest a PDF. A PDF gives a model text, but a relationship
may be implicit,
entity identity can be ambiguous, and provenance and
context may be difficult to reconstruct.
But a semantically published article can provide this.
It can instead expose explicit meanings, entities,
relationship, and provenance. And this does
not remove the need for AI models. It gives them much
better structured material to work with.
AI readiness is therefore a consequence
of good semantic publishing.
But
to conclude, the real challenge is no longer proving that this is possible
for one article. The challenge is making it work at
scale.
We need to move from individual articles or individual publisher
towards a broader
convergence in the community. That means making standards,
PIDs, production workflow, part of the
normal academic publishing practice.
The legacy literature will continue to require extraction, but
every new publication can avoid adding to the backlog we already
mentioned.
So the message I would like to leave you with is, don't
just liberate biodiversity literature, but publish
it liberated. Thank you.
So now, thank you, Chris, for this very
cool talk,
which explains much better what I tried to say. So it's good.
Now, the
third talk by Donna Dagosti is being held by Laurence.
So now it's an error in the program.
So it's not Donna Dagosti, but Laurence will have the talk.
Otherwise, we are just
listening to Donna all day, so we thought it was better.
Okay, so I'm going to talk about digital native species
workflow and how this will help us to transition
from PDF liberation to XML first-based
workflow in terms of publication.
We already said so
several times, but we are going to repeat ourself today.
We don't know what we've already discovered.
Despite centuries of
scientific observation and million of pages digitalized,
the data remain locked in PDF or
in a narrative unstructured.
So, and what's worse, as Chris shown, we still
produce
legacy, so to speak. We still produce
content that are
imprisoned in PDF.
Scientific publication is part of the research cycle.
This is particularly true in taxonomy.
However,
from the moment we collect a specimen on the field to a moment we publish
something about this specimen, it takes on average
21 years.
So it means that we have to do something very
urgent. We have to scale up biodiversity description.
We have to speed up the discovery of new species.
We have to shorten the time from collecting to
publishing, and we have to monitor the impact of what we are
doing, of course. So we propose several action to do
so. First of all, we will see how digital bond species
will allow us to have digital bond data more accurate.
We are still working on massive and accurate ferization of data,
so still with the legacy to be made available, but also with
the prospective to make sure that this data is made available as soon as it
is published. One important thing we have to do is to
link taxonomic names to the related data in
publication and give context to those names.
And finally, we will provide some dashboard to
monitor the impact of what we are doing and making sure that we are
doing it well.
So, the vision we have is to build the planetary knowledge
base, and we can see in the left,
in the dataset, most datasets present here are within
literature. So within literature, you can find data about the collection,
or the genetic, or the acoustic observation so far.
So we really need to
make this data available to make sure that we can use it, and we
need to make it structured and machine readable.
Instead of that, we are getting this.
We are getting unstructured and disconnecting data with
access issue that doesn't help us to speed
up or scale up the
biodiversity discovery. So the old model is this
one. We do have data at the beginning of the
research process. We built our thinking with data,
and then we erased all this data, and we lost
them into PDF. So then we still have to
extract and rescue the data content within the PDF,
so we can push that into relevant databases.
So it means that from the beginning, we had data, and then we erased
it into the PDF, and we lost the data.
We have to reconvert it, so we make error when we convert it.
Instead of doing that, the idea with digital native
species is that we will provide the data input at the beginning
of the workflow, but we are going to link and structure this
data at the beginning of the workflow and still use those links
and make sure that those links continue to the whole workflow since the
beginning of the research to the publication, so we can
release data in structured format as outset.
If you want to know a bit more about this workflow of
digital native species, I encourage you to have a look on
this paper that has been
written this year, in 2026, that
explained the workflow more or less.
So basically, very quickly,
the conversion is this one. We convert one bulk
sample into a biodiversity knowledge graph, in which
every piece of information from the specimen is going to be linked to
all the information about the specimen.
So basically, we'll have an individual specimen linked
with the DNA barcode or the image or every
genomic taxa, data, sorry, about the specimen, and
everything will be then exported into JSON and
uploaded into Zenodo.
So from here, we do have the physical sample
that will be linked to the digital
specimen during the digital data production, and then it's going to
be analyzed, and then it's going to be put
into a manuscript that will be produced and
published at the end of the process.
And you can see the cycle
where I was talking about before, about the fact that
the publication is within the cycle of the research.
So from the publication, the publication will cite the treatment,
then the treatment will cite the publication as well.
We still have to adapt the publishing workflow that we
have to make sure that we can do that.
So we will have an XML-based manuscript with
all the semantic enhancement. So we will have
all the linked into the XML, and the idea is not to lose anything
from there during the editorial process with the inclusion of
identifier that we will have at the beginning of the process, not to
lose any link and make sure that the peer review process is done
the usual way, and then come back to the publishing output,
and we will be able to publish in multiple format
that will allow, of course, archiving and make the information
AI-ready,
avoiding all the hallucination that we can have in AI.
So once again, the new model will allow us to have
digital-born species linked with all the
data, so the physical specimen linked to the
digital specimen, and as soon as it's linked, it will go into
the workflow up to the publication itself, where we can
push all the relevant information into the databases the way
we are already doing for legacy, but without
any errors. So this workflow will have
multiple benefits. I'm not going to enumerate all the benefits
here, but just two benefits are clearly more
important than the other from my perspective here.
The first one is that with having XML First
journal production, we can have FAIR-born data
at the day of publication. So this is very important, and not
only that we release the data at the day of publication, we already
know how to do that with legacy or with PDF-born,
but the idea is also that it's trusted data.
Since they are published,
the data is already certified and curated, so it will
help us to avoid or to prevent hallucination
in AI-ready stuff.
So
here is the pros and cons from the three
workflow that we use. So the legacy, the born digital PDF,
and the XML First base. I'm not going to enumerate all that, but
just explicitly stress out some important
fact.
One of the big cons from my point of view in the legacy is the
OCR artifact that we have to crack, so it's
kind of difficult. Both legacy and born
digital share the fact that the publication is made for human
consumption only. So it means that we do have a
lot of errors cracking that and converting that
into data afterward. And
while in the XML First base,
the
data is controlled from the beginning and will follow the route
to the workflow until the publication, and the bidirectional
links in the published paper will be still there.
So what is a bidirectional link means that you target
data from your publication, and the targeted data will
also
link back to the source, to the publication.
So this is
both way doing. So all of those will
allow us to have some metrics and to measure the impact of
what we are doing. So to have a
better view of the impact we have, we can provide some
dashboards. So we have several dashboard available to
see
what the liberation of data can
h- Have as an impact for an institution, for instance.
So here it's an example for an institution.
So the corpus here is all the paper
authored by a researcher of an institution, and also all
the paper in which a specimen is sitting
from the institution. So we can see here, for instance, the
geographic coverage of all the material citation across the
world of the institution. We also have other
dashboard, and this is the GBIF seed portals for the
journal in Paris, and we can have visualization of our data
and see, for instance, the occurrences and the coverage, the
geographic coverage of the journals.
We have also other dashboard provided by Treatment Bank,
in which we can
see what happened with the data in the journal.
So we
can monitor also the life of the journal, see how many pages
are published, or how many new species are described in the journal, but
also monitor how much the journal is fair.
Meaning, how many of those data is already in
GBIF, is already on Zenodo, and so on, which is clearly
more important from my point of view than having an impact factor and
seeing if the journal is doing well.
Having a fairness of the journal is way more important.
And this is my favorite. I was talking about impact factor.
This is the proof that the impact factor is not a good measurement and
is not a good way of monitoring the
impact of a journal from our discipline.
You can see here that the average age of the
bibliographic reference in taxonomy is around 50
years. So the impact factor is calculated on two or five
years of citation. We can clearly show how much
it's irrelevant for taxonomy.
That's it. Thank you.
Thank you, Laurence. Now we
switch gears and listen to
This one doesn't work.
Oh.
It does not work.
No, it does.
Yeah, but it's not working.
It can work, but it's easier for you to...
Okay.
Yeah, I will do 15 minutes.
Yeah. So we are going to talk about literature triage,
which is more like
once the data have been published,
can you, in practice,
use it? Okay. That's the
mere idea.
It's really how to use the data or can you be even aware of
the data once they have been published.
So, I hope this is moving.
Yeah. So okay, the use case I report is,
there are two. The first one is focused on biodiversity in
Icelands, and this is supported by the BioMoney
project, which is a biodiverse project.
So there are many good reasons to work on
Iceland biodiversity. Actually, the idea is that the density
of
specific species in Icelands is way larger than in the continents.
Yeah.
And the second use case we will have is provided by the IPBES.
So they did this,
I would say, large scale assessment with different types of
invasive alien species, sustainable use assessment, and
value assessment. And the key question is that,
I would say, let's say you are interested in Iceland biodiversity or
something else,
and what tools could be there so that you
are sure you don't miss something relevant?
Of course, you can go with your search equations and in
Biodiversity PMC or somewhere else,
and write Iceland biodiversity. But with this type
of query, you are going probably to collect a fraction of what is
really the Iceland biodiversity literatures.
And you will collect also many things which are not at all
about the Iceland biodiversity. So here comes triage.
So the idea is that, okay, literature is a complete
backbone of science, okay? This has not changed.
It has been so for about 200 years. But the volumes
are really expanding. So what kind of automations
can come to change this
equation-driven search, in a sense?
So the back end is Biodiversity PMC, just simply because it provide a large
universe. Okay? But as we mentioned this morning,
now we are also swallowing part of OpenLX, and that's not really the
problem, what is the initial collection.
Of course, it play a role, but we can discuss that.
The only thing here that it's large. It's larger than PubMed.
It's also all the taxonomic treatments.
It's
many journals like the Pentom journal or Setup journal, which
are not into PubMed, so it's large. This is what I can say.
So the idea with triage is that-
Instead of searching this collection with your equations,
then you prepared a small set of the paper that
are relevant given your project. Okay, so you provide with
hundreds or a couple of hundreds of papers that are relevant
for the scope of your project. And then the system will swallow
these hundreds of papers, and it's going to build
binary classifiers to then, in the future,
split
the universe of biodiversity PMC into relevant
or non-relevant papers. So in practice, you end up with this type of
digest. So these are all the paper published between
April 2020 in 2026 and April
26. So it's about a week of all the publication
that were shown into biodiversity PMC.
Then you can click on the views, and then you have a landing page.
So here it says that
in this collection here we are in Medline, there has been
976 papers that have been screened, and of
course, the top papers, so these papers here, for instance, if
I can maybe, yeah. This paper, for instance, it has a very
strong score. This is
99% sure it's a paper about Iceland
biodiversity. So just by reading the title, you see that probably we
are right. Okay?
And of course, if you go scroll down the list, at the end, you will have
papers which have words like biodiversity, Iceland,
but they would speak about completely different stuff, believe me.
Okay, so this is triage. Then you have facets to navigate them.
That's the usual one. You can-- All these annotations that we reported this
morning, all the annotation coming from
ORFO, all the annotation coming datively from PlanZ and the like.
Okay, so now what about how good are these systems?
So I can report on this evaluation that we did for the IPBES and
the Iceland. So these are the volume of
data we worked on.
Let's say the gold standard, if you want.
Okay, so here you have a sort of balancing of the categories.
So this is for IPBES. You see that
the positive are much larger than the negative.
Actually, it's a common issue. People curate the positive and keep the
positive, and they forget about keeping track of the negative.
But we should keep track of the negative.
That's a very Hegelian discussion.
So, okay, this is
the
language modeling engineering. Maybe I will not get too much
into detail here. So we apply the-- So the first
recommendation is that if you are interested once in your life in 10
years to build a triage system, keep track of the negative.
So this is the results we obtain
for
the IPBES. So the best results-- Sorry, it's ringing.
The best results are obtained
with
an ensemble of birds. So it's a type of language model
which are
very efficient and relatively compute cheap
compared to your favorite chatbot or whatever.
It's about 3,000 times cheaper,
and it's usually a bit better. So, you have no reasons to
use a
very large language model, which are generative.
So,
okay. So this is where we are, and someone asked this morning
about the biodiversity language model. We tested them.
They did not improve.
Okay, so these are the results for the Iceland now.
So the
precision is in the range of
90 or 92. This is consistent with the
inter-rater agreement. So
don't be confused. It doesn't mean that it's better because that's at the
level of the benchmark, but it means that we are competitive with humans.
Humans would agree with what we judge is good, and
that is what is important.
Okay. We can look at all the distribution, but the key message is really
that we can do the same performance like the human curators.
Well, and then we tested with different
birds, Roberta, BioBert,
many of them. But the ensemble is combining them all together.
This is the result for the IPBES.
You see that the macro average is even more impressive for IPBES,
which is probably the
task is maybe slightly simpler.
It's also true for the Kappa. So even human would agree more with the
IPBES datasets than for the Iceland biodiversity. That's it.
Okay, so conclusion.
So
there are some aspect-- Oh, I did not put that in detail, but of course,
the challenge is different if you are working with
value assessment than from the other one, you see. You have more agreement here.
So probably invasive alien species, you get a higher
consensus than sustainable use assessment.
This is just observation from the IPBES data.
And then in general, so doing triage at scale is
effective, and it works. And now if you want to know about the
detail, what it costs, I think, say it's a couple of person months to
train the model. Okay, so
one or two person months. And then the hosting is probably a
few thousand bucks a year,
and the total investment is roughly 25K. Okay?
So it makes sense if you have a recurrent task.
So if you do curation of
mountain biodiversity, or if you do curation of something that you
will do in a continuous way, it would make sense to invest
25K.
So just a few words about the next steps.
So one of the challenge is to grow the universe.
That's why now we are moving to swallow OpenAlex and Unpaywall.
Actually, probably more Unpaywall than OpenAlex because Unpaywall
is still free.
And then, of course,
we can still use
large language model,
but not the way you would do that in an interactive way,
not as a chatbot, but we can use large language model to
generate the regular expression
patterns that we are going to apply
to the corpus. I will show you with example now.
And of course,
what we try is to have some frugal AI, not because we want to
save the planet,
but because it's really costly. I don't know if you really do at
scale
this model, but it can be tens of thousands
of euros. For a group like mine, it will be
200K a year. So I need to use this frugal
AI
just for costs, okay?
And none of the costs that you guys pay for Claude are the real
cost.
Don't forget that these company are not at breakeven and they
subsidize, they support your real work, okay?
That the cost will expose by a factor of 10 or more.
Okay, so what we want to do is to guide
post-triage. So once you have done your triage here,
you are happy with this, what can be done more to support the
curation? And these are the next steps I will show you.
I will probably only show you the general concept.
So the general concept is that,
let's say you want to annotate-- This example here is coming from an
experiment we are doing in Spanish for the Spanish
government, where they want to track for the
biodiversity evaluation made by
private companies, in fact, okay?
And the idea here is that you have all these
Spanish sequence, okay? And you want to turn
these few examples into keywords.
Or you want to turn these few, these are
like solar and wind energy
facility and stuff like that. So you want to have project types,
you want to find species names, different type of species
names from eagles to,
I don't know, Canis lupus. And then the same, you have
a few habitats that you are interested, wetlands,
riparian, swamps, whatever.
The same for the temporal entities, the fieldwork,
the surveys, effort, method,
and of course, the biodiversity assessment.
So you gather your set of keywords, like 50
keywords, and then you ask your favorite
large language model to generate patterns like verb
plus nouns, regular expression, then you swallow
dictionaries from GBIF, and then you get something that is more structured.
So, okay, I will show you the GUI. So the first GUI is like
ranking. I already have shown this.
And then the next one
is like you have all the evidence that you want to extract from
this paper. So they might be here you have different color codes.
These are species,
these are fieldwork, these are location.
And here, the last one is an option.
You can even have open questions. This is where you have chatbots,
in a sense. So it's a bit
small, but what we have is that we have, for species recognition,
we have a precision of 99%. So,
this
one, for instance,
Bubo bubo.
And then you can have, of course, this is the
vernacular name. And then you can see that it's a
nocturnal species, and so on.
But so these are the species that you get with all the match.
So you can click there. For instance, you have 10 occurrences of that one.
You can click there, and it will take you to the right passage.
And of course, this is true for species, it's true for fieldwork, and
all these different entities in this particular report.
So you can navigate
back and forth between the full text.
Okay, these are very long papers, like 100 pages.
And what has been extracted by the model here, okay?
And then the last piece is the question answering.
So you can really
provide a question. The question can be about location,
province, protected areas,
any type of things,
surface, and so on. And this
is completely interactive, okay?
So you have some question can be predefined, okay,
and some are not, okay? So this is, I think, the future of the
triage.
And at the end, of course, you need to extract all this.
And to extract all this different stuff, we will rely
on this BIO-C. So the BIO-C is a sort of JSON, and it's very rich
because you can almost store everything at every
offset level. So you will say that not only you have
this, okay, you have a certain location which is
Moclín in the province of Granada in Spain, okay?
Not only do you have this, but you know that this statement is between this offset
here and this offset here, okay? So you can even
ground the evidence in the body of the paper.
It's a micro, I would say, nano publication or whatever you want,
okay? And then you explore this record. And that's it.
So that's in a nutshell. Okay.
We have very good results also for this different type of
triage system.
We believe we are ready to move to production.
The velocity is really impressive.
It's 28 milliseconds per document.
I don't know if you see how slow your favorite LLM is, but if you
ask him to wallow 100 pages,
it's already taking
a lot of compute.
I think I'm done with the
triage,
if that still can move. And the future is agentic
triage. So it's going to be very similar, but each of
these services that I
described here, they will be supported by the completely different agents that can
be used individually. Today, you have an API,
but you cannot download the agent.
So the future is that everyone can download his own agents to have his own
instance, but it's going to take
another few months to have it.
Thank you very much for your attention, and these are all the guys that
contributed.
Okay. Now this is our value tool.
Go back a little bit and listen to why a lot of the questions come up
where Patrick was.
Okay.
Welcome, everybody.
You're seeing a rare species in front of you
considering this conference.
Let me start. I'm a user of the data. I'm not a producer.
I'm not working for a library, not for a museum.
Secondly,
for me, biodiversity is something completely different than for you,
for the taxonomists.
I'm an ecologist. These species exist.
They are also using taxonomic data, but they're needing much more
detailed data. We had a nice talk recently in a previous session by Emily Paschke,
looking at how to look at interactions, how to extract information about
interaction between species. These are the kind of information which is
needed for ecologists to really make that whole
ecosystem usable for them. And this information,
this approach of having it usable to be able to look into the PDFs
is absolutely crucial.
So
I'm involved in IPBES. Who knows what IPBES is?
Okay. IPBES is, to put it easily or
succinctly,
the counterpart to IPCC just for biodiversity
and ecosystem services.
So
one of their tasks is to create assessments about existing knowledge
to certain topics. One of them was a global assessment.
There were these assessments Patrick was talking about, about sustainable use
of species, invasive alien species, and so on.
Existing knowledge. They're not creating new knowledge, but they're using existing
ones, so literature plays an absolutely crucial part in
their line of work.
Up to recently,
looking into the past, what was done, Web of Science was used, Scopus
was used. The searches were done mainly through the web interface.
It takes time. I was involved in the first one, which was using the web
interface. It was a tedious exercise,
error-prone,
not really reproducible.
So there is no transparency in doing these searches
via the web interface. And transparency is
extremely crucial for IPBES because these assessments are
approved by the governments. So there's a panel of all of the
governments, and they are approving it. They will look into the details.
So it needs to be absolutely transparent.
What happened? Why are we not at that stage luckily anymore?
Well, in 2020, IPBES decided or adopted
a data management policy. One of its key points really was
that transparency. That transparency is essential
for IPBES products.
We have now
these data management reports where the management of the data is
detailed. From the beginning, the source data is specified, how it is
processed, the code is available.
That whole line from the source data to the final
product, the figure,
the table is detailed in these data management reports.
At around that time,
also, we discovered that there is something else apart of
Scopus and Web of Science. OpenAlex was mentioned already.
And we did some comparison.
It's compiled in that little white paper, which is updated
regularly. And
essentially,
it turned out OpenAlex is an extremely, extremely viable
alternative for IPBES compared to Web of Science.
OpenAlex is open by design.
It is free to use. We can discuss it in a second if you want to, Patrick.
You don't need a subscription. You just have to register,
then you get a certain amount for free, and that is enough for
most tasks. So normal users don't really have to pay for
it.
And the data and code, the data for their website, for all
of the
identification of topics, what they are doing, everything is
openly available.
The same applies to their data.
So you can download the whole data snapshot,
and
they started recently to provide that whole data snapshot, not only in
JSON format, but in Parquet format.
In other words, you
just download it, and you can use it from your scripts. You can read it directly.
You can work with it.
So you have the graphic user interface to do some stuff.
You have an API, which is
relatively easy, nice, forward to use, but extremely powerful if you
want it, if you need it.
And
you can download the data for more complex analysis.
And just a side note for cost,
we looked initially into using Web of Science for licenses and what we've
done, for example, for the transformative changes assessment.
The licensing costs for that one year would've been more than a
million.
So
not
possible for IPBES or I wouldn't say for any
institute.
So where are we now?
We are now in a stage where the API is used mainly for searches.
So our searches are defined in code.
They're not on the graphic user interface anymore.
Oops, wrong button.
We are able to manage
large datasets on a desktop computer,
4.5 million works.
We downloaded via the API and worked with it.
In addition to the standard keyword searches,
we are also doing snowball searches.
We are following
the citation graphs, identifying papers which have
cited or were cited in the papers. Extremely powerful
for focused searches where you want to
find an environment around them.
But there's still a gap,
and I think it was outlined enough, I don't have to go too much into data.
There is
lots of data in the articles themselves, which is
not exposed via the metadata and the abstracts.
And luckily, most of the papers have abstracts in
the biodiversity
literature. So we are lucky ones. But
during the time I'm working with it, Open Alex, they already had to reduce the
number of abstracts they could provide radically,
which I think is
completely the wrong way.
Another problem is
languages. Keyword searches,
they are based on languages. They're looking for the exact words, so there's no
translation happening.
So if you want to have literature, which is in another language, you have to
translate your search terms. For that one you need experts because it is not as
easy as putting it in an LLM to let it translate it.
So
these gaps are really limiting
the efficiency of IPBES and working with it, and also to use the
data which is inside the papers.
Another gap which hasn't been mentioned yet, but which is also crucial in the
context of IPBES is
grey literature. Grey literature, non-scientific literature,
some say non-peer reviewed literature.
These are reports, UN reports, lots of that stuff.
Extremely valuable source,
extremely difficult to find.
How do you get hold of them?
So
these are two big gaps
which now coming to the way forward, how the library scope could change that one
actually could be addressed by the library scope, the extraction of the data,
the semantic tagging of the articles,
the
digital-born publications,
and so on.
This would make the work of IPBES finding the literature,
compiling the corpuses, and not only of IPBES, but of everybody else who
is using literature
much more efficient.
And
essentially it would make it possible not to only search for keywords
and information in the metadata, but also for content in the
paper themselves. Filter it by content.
So you can look for facts, you can query by facts.
What I find an intriguing perspective is the idea not only to
follow the citation networks, but doing a snowball
search on your knowledge graph.
That you can follow certain concepts and identify new
areas where you haven't thought about,
which are contributing to that one, which are using these concepts.
And last but not least,
if the library scope manages to ingest grey literature as well, that
would be one source for scientific
literature as well as
certain group of grey literature.
Obviously, it cannot ingest the whole of the internet, but there are
large number of sources, and Open Alex is working on that at the moment.
They're expanding dramatically
to also ingest articles, grey articles
from sources like UN and other organizations.
Yeah.
I think that was everything which already was discussed in the previous
presentation, so I'm not going to go into that one.
Just one point which I would like to raise is
necessity and speed.
You mentioned that, Laurence, that it is much faster if they are born
digital, these publications. That's a very important point.
But from the perspective of IPBES as well,
it is very important to have
literature for a certain topic available.
And to bring that literature into the Library Scope, into
Biodiversity PMC,
would be a very crucial step towards making it usable.
Because
as far as I know, you've given the numbers,
Biodiversity PMC is small compared to Open Alex.
Hopefully, that gap will be filled.
So something like ingestion on demand, where you
can identify papers in Open Alex
which you would like to access or work with, you need.
Then providing that information to the Library Scope,
and that one is ingesting these papers on demand.
And then ideal case,
a week later, you get a report, your data is there. You can use it.
You can search on the data which is inside of these.
I think that would be an approach which would help a
lot in these times now with biodiversity crisis and where speed
is really, in so many areas, absolutely crucial because that
information is needed. It would help
in so many areas to move more efficiently forward and to save
resources.
Thank you.
Thank you, Rainer. Now we move to the last use
case on
how to use the state-- the data in publications.
Paul.
Thank you very much, Donat.
Okay, so yeah, we're finishing up with another use case example,
and here, focusing mostly on the legacy extraction rather than
the born digital publications for the time being.
Here, with the specific use case of
extracting through text mining approaches, species trait
information, to be able to bring that into our species
distribution modeling and our species richness modeling.
So just to, by way of introduction,
what we've been talking about here from the literature is really kind of
the way to make links. We talked a lot about links.
We talked about bidirectional links, et cetera, between what we
understand at the central core here is our species
concept, and then everything we know about that species, and these can
be broad generalizations, or they can be really specific items of
information. And here on the one side, I have the
genetic genomic information because that's the kind of direction that I've been
coming from in my own research, but on the other side here, talking about the
literature. So if we can make the connections to the treatments,
for example, where the species are described and revised, but also
other biodiversity-related publications that give additional information
about the species, then within those publications, can we use some of the
approaches that we were seeing
presented today to begin to extract information about
life history traits, for example,
distributions, et cetera?
Yes, we can.
But this is a complicated process, and for a limited
number of taxonomic groups where there is a huge amount of research interest,
there has been a lot of effort into extracting this, usually
manually from the literature, and putting it into
curated catalogs of trait information, which it's an
amazingly laudable work. But it's just not
scalable in terms of the number of species that we're thinking about and the number
of traits that we would eventually like to reach
into these databases.
So
we saw in the previous presentations now, I hardly even
have to promote the technical motivation here, right?
We have these workflows
that are now able to take the information that are
locked in the PDF prison,
restructure it, extract it, link it, and publish it,
but publish it in a machine-actionable format.
And so
this is, first of all, getting it out there and making it machine-readable.
Then the next step is labeling what's
machine-readable in those texts.
And so here again is the technical motivation side of things.
So given that we now have access to here, for example, a
taxonomic treatment, can we identify the species,
the traits, and the value,
in its simplest form, a triple of information, and store that in
some sort of accessible database where we can make it available to
researchers to answer whatever question they might be using?
And here, because I'm asked to present a use case, this is
where we want to go with extracting species trait information
from the literature.
And this is related specifically to species distribution modeling.
So in some of my other projects, like Biodiversity Meets Data,
we are working on making lots of different environmental
datasets and observation datasets available with increased
curated metadata to feed into some of these more powerful
species distribution modeling efforts
But essentially, the baseline is we're taking species observation
data plus these abiotic layers, so
information about the landscape, the environment, and then we're trying to
predict. There it's called suitability maps, but you can find lots of different
names for this kind of thing. Species distribution, where you think would be a good
or not a good habitat for species X or species Y.
And then we can also think in future scenarios.
So we're thinking about what's going to happen to different taxonomic groups or
even individual species given, for example, climate
projections.
Now, the motivation here to bring in
the
species trait information is on top of this
layers that are the standard methods for species distribution modeling, what
if we had information about feeding ecology or
habitat preferences?
And
complementary to that, what if we also had information about
genetic structure, genomic structure, population structure?
So the subdivisions of populations within
a given species.
And if we can add those layers, so we can add a species trait layer,
then we can begin to enhance our modeling with joint species distribution
modeling. So species A likes to feed on species B,
let's model species A together with species B to have an improved
outcome of the predictive power of our model.
And the same with the genomic species distribution modeling.
This
almost cartoon-like example, if you treated that as a single
unit genetically, you're going to get a very different answer than if you
have information here telling you that, in fact, there are probably at
least three more or less distinct genetically populations
within this species. And so that's obviously going to influence the result of
your species distribution modeling at the end.
So this is the example of the motivation.
In summary, extracting the species trait
information to get information about interactions, habitats, life
histories, to feed that into the species distribution modeling and the
taxonomic richness models. But at the same time, also looking at
discrimination analysis from available genomic data to
identify populations, subpopulations, et cetera.
Also dark taxa, where we are confusing one species that's actually six species,
and how does that influence our modeling?
And perhaps, I don't know, maybe this is a bit far-fetched for the moment, but
also thinking about adaptive potential.
So going back to that, thinking about future scenarios under different climate
predictions.
And in between these two layers, we also have some questions about taxonomic
name evolution. So how does the certainty or
uncertainty of a given taxonomic name influence
our ability to use traits for the modeling and influence
our ability to
understand particularly dark taxa?
Where instead of previously talking about subpopulations, we're actually talking
about separate species that are just not yet recognized as separate
species.
So, I think it's fairly clear where our objectives are with this
project. The first one is really being a use
case for demonstrating the value of extracting trait
information from the scientific literature.
Bringing also the genomic side of things.
So what can we do with the available data?
What gaps do we need to fill in order to be able to use this for improved
modeling?
I mentioned the taxonomic name evolution.
Where is it a problem? As in where in the tree of life is it a
problem? Where is it less of a problem?
And finally, of course, to use all those three outcomes to
improve our ability to model species distributions and future
scenarios, and also understand the evolution of possible
taxonomic richness.
And so in this Swiss National Science
Foundation-funded project, we have chosen a couple of different
taxonomic groups, some where we think there should be excellent literature
and hardly any problems with taxonomic name resolution, and
others where we have more species and more
uncertainty, so those amphipods.
And probably less literature associated with it, fewer taxonomic treatments.
So we have a range of different taxonomic groups to be able to test the impact
of being able to extract the trait information, analyze the genomic information,
and try to use that to inform the modeling.
And so from the literature mobilization side of things, we're using
existing taxonomic treatments from Plazi and Treatment Bank, but
also trying to search for and identify and prioritize
publications that are out there that could feed into our system that have not yet
been digitized. So,
trying to prioritize documents that will help us to answer our
specific question here.
And also looking at the newly mobilized publications books.
We talked about gray literature as well.
So, Field Guide to the Bats of Switzerland.
How do you access that in a machine-readable format?
It's a great book, but
we need the computer to read it, not us to read it.
Ignore exactly all of the values on this plot because we are still working out some
technicalities. So, for example, when you query GBIF API for the
400 amphipods, it blocks you unless you've also pre-registered and
stuff like that. So there are occurrence data for amphipods.
But this is our starting point, and so you see the heterogeneity
across the different groups that we're looking at.
And then, our priorities are to identify, digitize, and annotate
the missing taxonomic treatments,
and taxonomically relevant publications.
Building this text mining workflow, which I'll show in the next slide,
including gray dataset searches, not only for the traits but
also for genetic information. A lot of this stuff is sitting in supplementary
materials that never makes it into the archive repositories that could be
useful for this kind of work. And starting with our baselines where
we don't have the trait information and we don't have the genetic information, so
we can try to make the comparison from the before and the after.
So I won't go into a huge amount of detail because this is really the use case, not
the technology, per se, of the text mining workflow.
It's fairly standard. In this case, we're
building on something we did previously that was really focused on arthropods.
But of course, you need your dictionaries, you need your vocabularies, you need
your starting points to then identify the publications of
interest, start to do your entity recognition
with some machine learning training on gold standard annotations.
So where we get communities to annotate publications
manually and curate them, and then compare them so that we can have the testing
and the training datasets, so we can actually show
F1 max, we can show performance of the models on
papers that it hasn't seen before.
All that feeding into the scientific community, and ideally having a bit of a
feedback loop at some point
to correct, improve, and reject wrong annotations, for
example.
So I had to put one example up there just to make it realistic
to understand. So this species of arthropod have been
reported as parasitoids of Euphtheciidae of
Bletidae. Now, here we have a species, or a group rather,
a taxonomic group, which is in this case a value, not an arthropod,
because it is the target of this triple relationship between arthropod,
trait, and value.
This is actually quite a simple example.
But just to get the machine learning models to get this kind of thing
right, it takes a lot of work and a lot of feedback.
But this is what we're aiming for in a real text world situation.
And so
I'll try to conclude now because we're running out towards the end of the time of
the session. But just to come back to this,
why am I speaking about this today?
So it's really
piloting some examples of extracting trait
information from the literature, but for a research question at
the end of the day.
So
we would hope that by
attacking
the literature side of it now to bring it together with the genomic side of it, we
are unlocking, at least for our target taxa in our
target geographic regions, for our target questions at the moment, which are
focused on species distribution modeling,
to make a really strong demonstrative use case
example of the importance of this.
Because I think,
well, we were discussing this morning and probably in other sessions throughout
this conference of how hard it is to persuade our
funding agencies to support fundamental
infrastructures.
And all of that digitization, mobilization,
liberation, and annotation are mostly considered
infrastructure tasks, if you like.
And so only when we can show use cases like this that
demonstrate the added value of that underlying infrastructure, we can
begin to move forward as a whole community trying to extract
information from the literature.
So I hope that was a meaningful use case that you can take home and use
as an example in your own talks in the future. Thank you very much.
With that, we are running out of time now.
So I hope we had a very interesting
afternoon. You're inspired, and you see a little bit where, in which direction
this idea of Libroscope, the direction of
making data from publication really accessible is moving.
So the DSIS roadmap is not, and it's not meant to
be
a form in the organization. So the idea is really to
have these gatherings and actually motivate you and talk to each
other, and hopefully we can build together institutions, multiple
hopefully, for depositing
all the
baseline data we need to all the processing.
So with that, I wish you
a good afternoon,
and thank you for being here.
And thank you to Steve.
My name is Paco Pando, and I'm organizing this symposium
together with my colleagues, Serge Goffas, Ritt
Long.
Hi.
Victor Yeung.
There.
Pierre Bonnet, and Alexander Monroe.
Most of us are also involved in the work
you will hear about today.
For more than 30 years, the World Geographical Scheme for Recording Plant
Distributions has given our community
a common, concise way of describing where species occur.
It is available, the most widely used Tadwig
standard after Darwin Core.
Bodies such as the FAO or the IUCN
rely on it, and also do scientific projects and collection around the world.
But the world has changed since its last edition
in 2001. Borders and names have changed.
The scheme never covered oceans, and it was only
ever about plants. So in 2001,
a new interest group was created, Geo schemes,
with two task groups, one for the terrestrial domain and the other for the marine
domain.
Our goal was to produce a World Geographical Scheme for
recording species distribution, not only plants, covering land and sea
for every taxon. Today, we will look at the two sides of
the world, how the new scheme is being built and how it is
used in practice.
We have four presentations for this
symposium.
We allocate 12 minutes for each,
questions included, and hopefully, we might have time for
discussion.
You will see that we are counting on you to refine and to
put us in the right direction for the final steps in the production of
this updated standard.
And with this, we start. Our first speaker,
Serge. You have the floor.
Thank you. You hear me with microphone? Okay.
Good afternoon, ladies and gentlemen.
Well, since I am the first one to open this Geo Scheme
symposium, I will first start telling how
all this came along and then also
tell you about the outcomes that we are expecting
from our project.
So this started, the marine part
at least, started within the World Register of Marine
Species. Maybe many of you have already heard of it.
It's a
database curated by 300-plus experts in
marine taxonomy,
which is hosted at the Flanders Marine Institute
in Oostende, Belgium,
and continue the first project, which was a European
Register of Marine Species, but later were extended to the world.
So there,
the fact sheets
for the species,
the basic information is the accepted name,
and then a list of synonyms which all guide you to the
accepted name, so you have no excuse not to use the right one.
There are literature reference to the original
description and other relevant things.
There are images, and
there is a distributions tab, and that's where
it hurts because,
people have been using haphazard geographic
units. So it starts from the northern end of the pier at
Oostende to Northwest Atlantic Ocean or
circumtropical or things like that.
Or even
sometimes
land masses that
display as a country because somebody put in United States
and then it... So we were not happy at all with
this.
And we started looking around for something better.
And of course, our attention was called on the
existing Tadwig scheme for the land distribution, so
the World Geographic Scheme, which Paco will explain in
more detail now how it's going in the third talk.
And this was really the idea we wanted because it's
country-wise, so what end users want ...
is to be able to retrieve national checklists, and sometimes we get the
information in a way that we know the country, but we don't know more.
And the scale of the units is reasonable
for having something worldwide and not too complicated, but not too
rough
on the display. So
we started looking around. Well, we're not starting completely from
scratch. And started looking around at the many
regionalization schemes existing for the sea.
And for this, we're counting on a very large repository, which is also
hosted at the Flanders Marine Institute, and Britt Longeneville will
introduce you in the next talk, so I'm
skipping this point. So one of the
items in this repository is the exclusive
economic zones of the world countries.
So that's a good starting point. And for many countries,
that's
what we want. Belgium,
Guinea,
okay, that's all right. But many countries are complex
with different maritime facades or are too big, like Brazil or
India or whatever. So those need to be split to
smaller units in order to be functional for our
purpose.
So that was one starting point, but it needed
elaboration.
Another starting point would have been,
you maybe know that paper by Spalding and coworkers in
2007, "Marine Ecoregions of the World." So
it's a very empirical
subdivision of the world's littoral
areas in something like, I think it's 230 or
whatever,
biogeographic, more or less, but not data-driven,
but empirically designed units. But
the problem with MEOS is that they completely
ignore
country borders. So this is sub-Saharan
upwelling. We said takes a little bit of southern Spain and southern
Portugal without any reason. And what do you do with a
locality
that falls here? So, okay, we were unhappy with
all those things.
Well, we are going to make something of our own, and then we will be happy with
what we elaborate for our purposes.
And that's what we started, well, in 2021, the interest group,
and
then in 2023, the two task groups, one for
updating marine, which Paco will present, and one updating
terrestrial and one for
launching marine. So
Nicolas Bailly, who was a
main scientist of FishBase, you might know, was also one of the
driving forces into setting the marine part.
And Britt joined from Marine Regions, and
without her, without Marine Regions, we couldn't go anywhere.
So we published
last year a paper describing the proposal in
detail. It
goes
to
level four units, so that's hierarchical, and then it gets up to 200
and something level two and five level
one units, which are the major oceans.
You don't have to
note down all this URL. If you just type in geoschemes
marine, you'll get immediately to the page on GitHub where the
proposal is posted. So that's what it looks like.
This is level two with colors, but
you can see on the map the outline of the level four
units for the coastal region. So the main idea is level one is
the major oceans. Level two is coastal
areas grouped by biogeographical regions, and the high
seas are another level two.
And the basic idea is that coastal areas are
always divided country-wise, so
they are
functional for retrieving local,
regional,
national checklists. For the high seas, there is very
little data-driven
regionalization, so we have been using a
large paper by Watling et al., which have
modelized the sea floor with a threshold at
3,500 meters between abyssal and bathyal, and within that, well,
we have the major basins and
major sea floor elevations. Okay.
So I'm not going to tell the project completely because otherwise
it's one hour. But
you can read the proposal if you are interested.
The next step is to turn this into a TDWG
standard.
And there, some things are straightforward, and some things
are awkward.
So straightforward that our units are concepts.
It's straightforward that
the codes that we have for every unit,
which is unique throughout the terrestrial and marine
parts,
can serve as a local name,
and the value of that codes can serve as a
controlled vocabulary string because it's unique
within the system.
Then the label, which is also something required.
Well, it's the full name of those units, like
Cabo Verde Economic Zone or Angola Basin or whatever.
So that's the human-readable name.
So that's easy. So the
problem is what do we do with
definition?
So definition, the
standards specification document read, it
must include the wording to describe the class property or
concept in words in English. So how do you
describe the Cabo Verde exclusive economic zone
in words in English?
We don't have a solution, so my idea is that
would it be acceptable to refer to an external
source like marine regions where there is a map,
and
say the definition is the area displayed on the map in such and
such area. So this here, we need advice from people
with more experience than I have in this
kind of things. Okay. So to-- Finally, I'm
in time. To conclude,
the expected outcome of this exercise is to have
an agreed set of reasonably sized
geographical units standardized for the display of
geographical distribution, well, in WORMS in the first place, but
for anybody who needs to do this. And it's
also a tool which allows cross-checking point
data, because we're not going to compete with GBIF and OBIS who have
point data drawn from museum collections.
We are going to have
data drawn from published literature statements of
occurrences.
And you can see there are places where GBIF has points,
but we don't have them because we consider it's another species,
and
places where
we have records from the literature and GBIF has no points because
nobody has entered the point for the Azores, not because the species does not
exist. So this is another
possible outcome. Then it's also a
useful tool for manual data mining of
distribution as they are published as maps in various sources
of literature.
It's a tool for the immediate-- When we're through, we can have
any taxonomic list for any country of the world
because the units are hierarchized, so
even if a country is split, we can always call the higher level
and have a complete
list of what's entered. But of course, it must be entered in the
beginning.
And finally, it's a fine tool for geo-unit based global
analysis. The average size of our units is in the
order of 100,000 to 500,000 square
kilometers.
People usually use five-degree grids.
That's 300,000 kilometers, so we're in the same
range. And
MIO, which are also used in global analysis, are much
larger because there are about 200 and something MIO against
577 marine geoschemes
units. Okay.
Well, that's basically it. Thank you for your
attention. Thanks to all the people who have
supported, helped in various ways since the
beginning of this project.
And, well,
any questions? Thank you.
Time for questions?
Yes, we have time.
Then we have time for questions.
Hi, I'm Malin, Swedish Species Information Centre.
Do you have a
year as a reference or will you pick any
occurrence point from a literature from any given time?
Or, I mean, backwards in history.
This is a spatial frame. In WORMS, we don't have a
specific frame for time, but
every entry can register the time of
first observation. By default, it's the date of the
paper from which it's drawn.
But if the paper
published in 2001 says this was collected in 1974, then
the date is--
There is a field for entering the date in WORMS.
Thank you
very much.
Any other question for Serge?
If not, we move on the program and our next speaker.
Brit.
Good afternoon.
I hope you can hear me.
No.
No? Okay. Can you hear me now?
Yeah.
Okay.
So hi, everyone. My name is Brit Lonnewele.
I work for Flanders Marine Institute in Belgium at the data center.
I have a huge imposter syndrome today because I'm
not a biologist or a taxonomist, I'm a geographer, so I feel a bit
of an odd duck. And the thing that I'm presenting is maybe also
not something that many other people are presenting today, but I do want to give
you a small introduction into marine regions which will be
the backbone for the marine geoscheme
that we are preparing.
Well, again, geographer, so maps.
I like to think that marine regions is based on three main
pillars.
What do we offer? On the one hand, we have a gazetteer of marine
georeferenced places. Then we have open datasets of
maritime boundaries. And then finally, we try to provide
access to relevant geospatial layers.
Mostly scientific,
of course, marine, and somewhat related to biodiversity too.
So what is a gazetteer? That is exactly the question that I asked myself when I
started that list eight years ago.
I would explain it to my grandmother as it's the ocean's phonebook, but maybe to
you, I can better explain it as the geographical
counterpart to WoRMS. So where you have the checklist for
the maritime species, I'm maybe saying this wrong, I tried to
pick up. But anyway, this is like the checklist for marine places.
So we're going to say, this is this type of place.
It's called this or this or this, so you can have synonyms.
This is where you can find it, of course, with some nice coordinates.
And then very importantly, we're going to give it a unique
and persistent identifier for unambiguous referencing.
In our specific case, this is called an MRG ID, Marine Regions ID.
Since the start of Marine Regions, we have now almost 65,000
features in our gazetteer, and we don't make up any
names ourselves.
We get them from authoritative sources, and those can be both
ecological classifications because, for example, the World
Geographical Scheme for Recording Plant Distributions is in there, has
been in there for a long time already.
Also, the Marine Ecoregions of the World, which Serge was referencing,
are in there.
But also other gazetteers, such as the gazetteer from
GEBCO or national gazetteers. New Zealand is in there,
Canada is in there. And we also try to map
them on each other because they often have the same feature in different
gazetteers, and then we give them one unique identifier so that you're all
referencing to the same feature with confidence.
And then what makes it very well suited for the work that we're doing with Serge is
that it has a hierarchical structure as well.
We can indicate parent-child relations within our gazetteer.
So feature A is a part of feature B, is part of feature C.
These sand banks are a part of the Belgian part of the North Sea, and the Belgian
part of North Sea is part of the North Sea, et cetera.
And so, for example, you see here, from the World Geographical
Scheme for Recording Plant Distributions,
the Norway level three feature, which then has a parent being
Northern Europe, level two, and then it also has a child being Norway,
level four.
So that's the gazetteer. And then another thing that we did
throughout the years, basically, again, to help WoRMS,
is to digitize
the UNCLOS regions. So the United Nations Convention
on the Law of the Sea defines several zones,
jurisdictional areas, such as the territorial waters,
internal waters, contiguous zones, exclusive economic zones, et
cetera. And so we have gone into all those legislations,
picked out the points, connected the lines, and then made the polygons so that they
can be used for research, for education,
and made those available on our website with a CC BY license.
We try to continuously update
those based on one hand, of course, if there's new legislation, or
if there's any court rulings, but we also get a lot of user
feedback, especially when they feel like something is wrong
or not in the interest of their own country.
And so these are also layers that we have on the one hand as just
shapefiles or GeoPackages or whatever that you can download, but they're
also in the gazetteer, so they have these unique
identifiers that you can refer to.
And then finally, a bunch of other relevant geospatial
layers.
I'm not going to go into all of them.
But, for example, what we also did is we went to the IHO
S-23 sea areas publication and digitized that
as well.
I know that now the S-130 project team has created a dataset for that,
but before it wasn't publicly available.
So that's on the website too,
Marine Ecoregions of the World. You can find it and download it and use it for your
own research. So all of those
resources together
kind of made us a
good partner, I guess, to work on this marine geoscheme.
And how are we involved in this? Well,
first of all,
we try to provide a data foundation.
So like Serge explained, we are providing these exclusive economic
zones, these IHO sea areas.
Also the MEOWS, so the Marine Ecoregions of the World.
We can provide those datasets to the interest group or task
group. And then we're also very closely involved in the
development and standardization.
So me and Serge have been in a very long mail train
over the last year, I guess, going back and forth like, "I want it this
way. I want it that way." And then we're going back and forth and making sure that
we're creating a standard that is both
as standardized as possible, but still user-friendly for people who would like
to
actually use it within WoRMS. And then finally, once it's
finished, the idea is that these units will become a part of Marine
Regions. We will, of course,
add them to our gazetteer, but then they will also be available for download
from our website. And it makes this also very easy, like, if there's any
updates to be done, yeah, we're right at the center of it,
so that would help tremendously
I'm standing here alone today, but this is not a work that I'm doing all
by myself. So I want to acknowledge the work, of course, of Serge,
but Marine Regions specifically.
I want to thank Laurence Whatley, Michelle Guevara, Bart Van Hoene.
They're excellent colleagues,
and I'm so proud that I can present the work that they're doing too.
And then also, Marine Regions is a United Nations Decade of Ocean
Science endorsed action. And so this work that
we're doing fits very well into the goals that we set out in
the course of this action.
Thank you very much for your attention.
Do we have time?
Yes.
So
questions for Britt?
Sorry, sir.
Not a question, but a comment about the hierarchy.
Usually when you have a hierarchy,
it's pyramidal,
but in the case of marine regions, you can have
alternative hierarchy. So our region,
Mediterranean EEZ of France
can have parent France and can have parent Mediterranean
Sea, which means that for the user, a query of
Mediterranean Sea will get it, and a query on
France nation will get it.
So
really, without marine regions coming in, we would have been going
nowhere.
Any other questions for Britt?
If not-
Thank you.
Well, thank you.
Do you want to give my mic to you?
So and next.
So this is the presentation.
Perfect.
Okay.
This is my turn now.
I'm Paco Pando. I'm based at the Royal Botanical Garden Madrid.
I'm convener of the
task group on the terrestrial domain for this schema.
So I'm going to talk about
the works of the task groups with a focus on the terrestrial
domain.
In the next minutes, we are going to go through
some of the core concepts of the schema,
a reference on how it is used,
and then on the current work.
What we are changing and what we are not changing regarding
the previous edition of the standard in 2001.
We will go through the
GitHub repository and then focus on
the actual issues and challenges that we have faced in this
work.
And I will finalize with a bit about the
decisions that we have taken, and then the decisions that we have
not taken, and that we need to solve before
putting the standard ready for the public review.
So the principles of
this schema. Well, it was the
brainchild of
D**k Brummitt, botanist at Kew Botanical Garden,
who conceived a system
to express,
in that moment, plant
species distributions, following
political borders, and also with a
phytogeographical point of view also in mind.
So to end up with units that could make sense from
the phytogeographical point of view.
It is a
hierarchical system of four levels,
in a way that
nationalist could
be
derived from it. And it is politically neutral.
So the decisions
made in the definition of the units doesn't carry any
political
weight.
Important to say that this
standard is not a biogeographical standard.
For that, there is another TWIG standard, which
is the floristic regions of the world following the work of
Tartajin. This is a prior standard that was endorsed
by TWIG
in the '80s,
so a long time ago.
Yeah. A reference how this standard is used.
Well,
it is used in a few global projects, such as
the Plants of the World, also used by the
IUCN in some of their products.
And
another important example are the green
database from the USDA Germplasm Resources Information System,
and also is very much cited and used.
Only since 2022,
got over 300 citations in scientific publications.
So as Serge and Britt has already advanced,
the work of this interest group was divided in the two domains, the
terrestrial and the marine domains.
The marine domain has to be
created anew following the principles of the
previous edition of the standard.
And the work in the terrestrial domain was more focused on
reviewing the political changes that have happened in these
years.
So this is an example of
how the scheme works. So first level, continents.
Second level is called regions.
Third level, botanical countries.
And then fourth level, just units within the
countries. For big countries such as Brazil or
the US or Chile, then
the
country is divided at the three level.
What we are changing.
Well,
from the beginning,
the
two task groups are working in coordination
to produce a schema with no duplicated
identifiers and also a system that make easier
to identify marine units and the terrestrial units.
In the 2001 edition, the reference was the Time
Atlas of the World.
In
2026, this is no longer appropriate, and we are
following a more concentrated schema such as the
UN naming conventions and the UN
country names database.
And then the definitions. In the 2001,
the definitions were based on the paper Times
Atlas.
For this
round, for this new update of the standard, we are
referring to actual polygons that anyone can
use and without interpretation.
The results of the works are, of
course, as
working within the TWG framework in GitHub, in their
own repositories. And there is the address of
the repository and an overview of the structure of it.
So,
as I said, the main work for the terrestrial
domain was to review the political changes in these 20
plus years.
So this is a few examples. At the end of the day, where
changes were needed, either in names or in
the borders, in the limits of the areas.
So, the terrestrial domain
units as they are now are
nine level one units, 52 level two,
369 level three, and 617
level four units.
At this time,
we consider that the work is complete.
Along the way, we have solved 34 issues
posed by either within the
core members of the group or outside.
And we are, at this moment, ready for doing the next steps and
finalization the standard.
So, well, I already have mentioned why we have them
already.
So now we are just checking that the
terrestrial and marine domain work well together and also working on
how the definitions, the polygons are going to be stored
and made accessible.
And so the next steps is just to
put some of the
tables in
open standards such as CSVs
and present it for public review
and finally get it ratified.
One slide on the
definitions for terrestrial units.
This has been the work of the
PlantNet team,
leaded by Pierre Bonnet,
who has already prepared a website and a repository for
all the units to be considered in the standard with a
very high level of detail, as you can see in this example about
the Canary Islands of some of the minor islands in the archipelago.
Then,
well, we need to define what
are going to be the normative body of the standard and what are going to
be
another associated materials that will make easier for the users to
use the standard.
So
the CSV definitely will be, and the units in
an open
standard, and then we will provide changes, a
crosswalk between the previous version and
the new one, and some
guiding documentation.
And with this, I
reach the end of the presentation and also this path in which we
have right now four, I call it, meta
issues. Issues that goes beyond the actual standards such as
shall we package this standard as just
one covering the terrestrial and the marine domain or two different
standards?
Where the
unit definitions, the polygons will live and be accessible.
For marine regions,
the preferred option for the group will be
the
marine regions. And for the terrestrial domain- Probably
we will be aiming for putting them in Zenodo.
Then also we have to decide the name, if we
keep the old
long
awkward acronym, or
move to a more easier to pronounce or to remember name such
as GeoSchemes.
And then the format of the polygons.
So again,
going
out of proprietary
formats such as
shapefiles, then
the GeoJSON or FlatGeo
are on the table. And with this, I've reached the end of the presentation, and
I'm not sure if we have
time for questions. Do we?
Questions?
Maybe not a question, but definitely a comment from my side.
About Zenodo, that's totally fine, but we will have to update the polygons that
were already marine regions for the terrestrial ones, so they will be there
regardless. Just mentioning.
We have the 2001 polygons.
Yes, but-
Now
... well, there is an issue with the precision and the detail of the
polygons.
So we need to upload-
Because we need to update what we have anyway
... anyway even if they are on Zenodo.
I think that the key point is to have one source for the normative
polygons,
and then propagate them wherever are needed.
When you said
it's not
political at all, but then you mentioned disputed territories.
Yeah.
So how do you decide which territories are legitimately
disputed?
We have taken different paths for
different cases. But
our guide was the
UN position.
So if the UN accepted,
for instance, Crimea
part of Ukraine, then ISO code goes to Ukraine.
Fortunately, Crimea is a botanical
unit by itself.
Yeah.
I won't comment on that.
Yeah. Sorry.
Can I ask what you used for the coastline?
Because it's much more detailed. What is the source data for the coastline?
Well, maybe Pierre
can answer that.
Sorry. It was based on OpenStreetMap data, and so we
clip the
coast coming from that sources.
Sorry.
Sorry, take.
So read the last one. Okay?
Sorry. Hi. It's more a comment than
a question. Is it that Guillaume Boddy, we as a poster on
BioDash,
asked me to tell you that he would be interested to discuss with you.
So if after the session you can go around this poster, it
would be-- He was in another session exactly at the same time.
Okay.
Sorry about that. That's really a quick one.
Thank you. And with this, we move to the last speaker of the session, Dr.
Liyum.
Not that one.
Yeah.
Hello, everyone.
I am Udhyangani Liyum from Royal Botanic Gardens,
Kew.
March this year, we completed a four-year mass
digitization project to create a comprehensive
digital catalog for horticultural and
scientific collections held at RBG Kew.
This project gave us the opportunity to strengthen our
data standards across collections.
So today, I will take you through how we
applied data standards for geography, and how
it enabled us to carry out a large-scale
geospatial analysis across collections.
So my presentation is more about application
of the Chadwick scheme.
Kew houses more than eight million plant and fungal
materials across 12 major collections.
Highlighted in yellow are living plant genetic
materials, ranging from living and
in vitro grown plants and propagules, live
seeds to tissue and DNA.
Highlighted in blue are micro slides,
dry and spirit specimens,
artifacts, illustrations, library books, and
archival documents.
During the digitization project, over six
million dry herbarium and fungarium
specimens were imaged, and specimen data were
transcribed.
EarthKeep Integrated Collection Management System is
one of the project output.
ICMS is implemented to manage data across
12 major collections within one system.
Previously, data were managed in isolated and
outdated systems with variable data standards.
In ICMS, data curation follows both
international and institutional data standards,
including TDWG, Darwin Core, and
established protocols from botanic gardens,
museums, gene banks, and DNA banks.
Then data-wise, data
includes all records migrated
through legacy databases,
and over six million records were added during
the mass digitization projects. Then other new
records are added through cataloging of new
materials.
Data entry is usually through bulk
imports or by manually record by record.
Geographic standards in ICMS include
assignment of ISO country and TDWG levels.
So this is at the higher level. We also record
other administrative levels and
locality description,
and also the geo coordinates,
altitude, and habitat details,
but those are not covered in this presentation.
So locality informations are
getting from the source data. So what is
available on the source material.
The source data could be typed or
handwritten in different languages,
may represent different periods and centuries,
and may contain historical and local references
to localities without specifying the country
or administrative divisions.
The section highlighted in red shows
how we record geography data at higher
level in ICMS.
These standards are applied either during
the initial data entry or through a
post-digitization work data flow.
So data entered by diverse range of
users, including the curators, the
horticulturalists, scientists,
students, and volunteers who may
have different level of familiarities with
this TDWG scheme.
So we needed a very simple and
user-friendly approach for data entry.
So in ICMS, when the user select the
ISO country,
there is a semi-automated process to populate the
corresponding TDWG levels.
For majority of larger countries, it populates
all four levels.
When the countries are large, selecting either state
level or province level at level four
populates the other levels. In complex
situations, it should be handled level
by level. Sometimes it may need
detailed geo references. For example,
transcontinental countries, where the geographic
area span across more than two continents,
the multi-country archipelagos,
and situation where geopolitical boundaries
had been changed.
Now about the digital records
and the results of what we have done.
So
in ICMS, currently, we have over
7.9 million digital records attached to a physical
object. As you will see, herbarium is by
far the largest collection, followed by fungarium.
Illustration collection at the bottom of the graph
is underrepresented in our analysis because it is at
early stage of digitization and not covered
by the main digi project. Otherwise, it has over
200,000 items. Other collections are
comparatively small, but each has a unique
role in biodiversity conservation.
So this is an overview of when these materials
were sourced from wild.
About 70% of our records
capture the year of collecting. The
dates span across five centuries.
The most collecting activity is from the
19th century onwards,
and there are noticeable dips during the World Wars,
and then the collection activity is slowing down
from late 20th century onwards. So
why I'm showing this graph is to
showcase that how heterogeneous,
how historically complex dataset we
are dealing with.
These are the collecting activity for individual
collections. As you will see, the first two graph,
the fungarium and the herbarium, has the longest
history. Our economic botany collection has
diverse range of ethnobotanical material, which is
dating back to before Common Era. For example,
this wreath of leaves is dating back to 1
BC,
although it was collected in 1888.
So we are trying to align this historical and
heterogeneous data set with a contemporary data
standard framework.
So this is the overview of the geographic coverage at
ISO and Tadbic level. As you will see, higher
percentage captured ISO code at level one and
two, but just over 50% captured level
three and four.
This is the continent-wise overview.
Geographic origins are predominantly from Africa,
followed by Asia tropical and South America.
Histogram shows the
collection-wise divisions, but herbarium and
fungarium data dominates. It is difficult to see the
pattern.
This is a little bit of more detail, this
heat map. As you will see, there is notable
differences across the collection.
Deeper the green is greater the number of
object, and the
gray column is where we don't know the continent, so it
could be a transcontinental country, so we have to go into
deep geo-referencing to allocate.
About 1.5 million records,
20% of the records. This is the
geographic coverage. So it's all
249 countries. Deeper the blue,
then greater the number of collection.
Some countries have over 100,000 to 500,000
collections.
As you will see, there are notable differences, but these are
for reasons. It could be physical or scientific reasons.
So a little bit about how we are sharing the data.
So the blue arrow shows data feeding
through
the main taxonomic name backbones we are using to
fungi and the plants,
including the nomenclature backbones.
For fungi, Index Fungorum and Species Fungorum.
For plants, we use IPNI and also
World Checklist of Vascular Plants, which is hosted in the Plants of
the World Online. So red arrow say where we share the
data. So Q Data Portal, our own product.
It is a project output, one of the output from
digitization project. Then we have a SFTP
website as well, and we also promote
samples, physical samples from our collection through our
website.
Then external portals, mainly the GBIF and
DisCoUK, but those are mainly for occurrence data.
We have living plant genetic resources where the data
go beyond the occurrence data. So for plant genetic
resources, for example, live seed,
we share the data through Genesis, through the Crop
Trust, and then the Seed Vault. I'm almost there.
Sorry.
So here we
share the occurrence data with Q Data Portal and then the
GBIF.
And my last slide.
So these are the key challenges. I already mentioned
the missing hierarchical data, historical data,
geopolitical boundaries change,
multi-country archipelagos,
absent geo-coordinate, language translations,
and
variable user familiarity with Tadbic.
It is one of the main actually thing.
So my thanks to the digitization project, is funded by UK
government and to members of the ICMS
team and everyone involved with making
this collection. Thank you very much. Sorry.
Thank you. We have three minutes for questions for Udayangani or any
one of the speakers in this symposium.
Sorry. It's an accident.
So those 50% who don't have a level four or level
three, is it because there is no locality at all, or
it comes from Basavamba and we don't know where this is?
Some have localities, for like
transcontinental countries, so we have to go
into the detail to find it out. So in the
mass digitization project, going into
detail wasn't one of the main aim because we have
four year, we had to do it quickly. So we have more
geo-referencing work to do. Sometimes there are local
references, but not saying the country.
So we have to go into detail, and somebody has to-
So you don't know which level two it is-
Continent
... or you don't know which level four.
Yeah.
Okay.
We have time for one more question.
And if not, then we bring to a close this symposium.
Thank you for attending it.
Well
And if the speakers and organizers can stay here together for a picture,
that would be nice.